<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Baptist and Independent Churches (so called) set on fire by a bright shining light revealed from heaven their pastors and teachers scorching in the flame of it, gnashing and blaspheming God in his temple ... / by ... Thomas Morford.</title>
            <author>Morford, Thomas, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11766936</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11766936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48789</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48789)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1489:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Baptist and Independent Churches (so called) set on fire by a bright shining light revealed from heaven their pastors and teachers scorching in the flame of it, gnashing and blaspheming God in his temple ... / by ... Thomas Morford.</title>
                  <author>Morford, Thomas, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48789:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48789:1"/>
            <p>THE BAPTIST AND Independent Churches (So called) Set on Fire. By a bright ſhining LIGHT revealed from Heaven. Their <hi>PASTORS</hi> and
<hi>TEACHERS,</hi> ſcorching in the flame of it, <hi>Gnashing</hi> and
<hi>Blaſpheming</hi> God and his Tabernacle; As their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples raſh and judging, herein recorded, do demonſtrate; which are anſwered for the vindicating of Truth, and the ſatisfying of the ſimple. In which they are found to be children of them who killed the Juſt, and have drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Cup of Fornication, who alſo muſt drink of the Cup of Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation at the hand of the Lord. Wherein alſo is an Exhortation unto all people, to examine themſelves in what ſtate and condition they are, and to meet the Lord by repentance, before that great Day of wrath that is come, and coming to overtake them, and they periſh for ever. In which all fleſh ſhall <hi>QVAKE</hi> and <hi>TREMBLE.</hi> Wherein alſo are ſome of the everlaſting Truths of God revealed, whereby all that have deſires and breathings after God, and to be partakers of the Divine Nature of Chriſt, and would be acquainted with the one Faith, and one Baptiſm, and with the way that leads into it, and the Kingdom of God, may be directed into it. Whereby every Particular may, by an infallible teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, according to the Law and Teſtimony, come to know whether they are in the one truth, and in it walking. In it alſo is a Word of Comfort to the <hi>IEWS.</hi> Likewiſe is ſhewed when all Carnal Ordinances (which ſtood in time and outward things, and had a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of time) ended to every one that believes, which were types and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and what they did prefigure, is proved by the holy Scriptures of truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one who is labouring and ſeeking the Redemption of all mankind in Chriſt Ieſus, who would not that any should perish, but come to the knowledge of the Yruth.</hi> THOMAS MORFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa 10 17.</bibl>
               <p>And the Light of Iſrael shall be for a fire, and his holy One for a flame, and it shall burn and devour his thorns and bryars in one day.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rev. 16.9,10.</bibl>
               <p>And men were ſcorched with great heat, and blaſphemed the Name of God, which hath power over theſe Plagues, and they repented not to give him glory, &amp;c. And they gnawed their tongues for pain.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſea 4.15.</bibl>
               <p>I will go, and reurn to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and they ſeek me in their afflictions.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the ſign of the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and
<hi>Windmill</hi> in <hi>Martins l'Grand.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:48789:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The heads of things contained in this BOOKE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>EDward Whale</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Waterford,</hi> his Doctrine—<hi>That none was ever free from ſin in this life,</hi> anſwered, <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Robert Carr, Baptiſt,</hi> Paſtor of
<hi>Clonmel,</hi> his Doctrine—<hi>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Scripture is the Rule of Life and Faith; and the more ſure Word of Propheſie, and the Law and Teſtimony</hi>) anſwered and confuted; and the true and perfect Rule and Guide, and the Law and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony ſhewed, what, and where it is. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>3. The ſaid Prieſt <hi>Whale,</hi> and Prieſt
<hi>Millard</hi> of <hi>Paſſage,</hi> affirming—<hi>That the Light within us is darkneſs,</hi> are here anſwered. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>4. An anſwer to <hi>Samuel Wade,</hi> Baptiſt-Teacher, who ſaith—<hi>He believes that the Quakers are under the higheſt deluſion, in mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying the Light within, in oppoſition to Chriſt without, and the Scriptures. p.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>5. An anſwer to an affirmation of <hi>Joſeph Parſons,</hi> a Teacher of the <hi>Free-willers,</hi> viz.—<hi>That God would purge the Tribe of Levi, to offer ſacrifices external, as of old: p.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>6. A raſh Judgement of <hi>William Lee,</hi> Baptist, Teacher and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Waterford,</hi> reproved and found falſe, and ſo proved according to the Law and Testimony; Wherein alſo is a true Testimony of the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Eternal Power and Spirit of the Lord in the work of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 24.</item>
               <item>7. An objection, <hi>That we obſerve not the Ordinances of Chriſt, as Baptiſm, &amp;c.</hi> anſwered, What that Baptiſm Matth. 28. was, viz. A threefold Miniſtration, by the ſame ſpirit. <hi>John's</hi> Baptiſm, a figure, fulfilled and ended. Baptiſm into Chriſt is another thing then that of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the figure. <hi>William Lee,</hi> and <hi>William Lamb,</hi> their groſs actions of violence, manifeſting their fruitleſs baptiſm. <hi>p.</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>8. Breaking of Bread a figure, carnal and periſhing, continuing onely till he came, who is come, the end of all figures. The form not to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in imitation without power. <hi>p.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>9 The Doctrine of Paſtor <hi>Hunt</hi> Baptiſt. againſt Perfection, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Of Imitation, which is Idolatry. Truth purifieth and perfecteth. A ſilence of fleſh muſt be, before God's Teaching can be received. But the Spirit being poured out, both Sons and Daughters may propheſie. <hi>p.</hi> 34</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48789:2"/>
            <head>To the impartial and unprejudiced REDER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHoever thou art that art enquiring after the Good old Way, to walk there, and haſt deſires to be directed therein, but art a ſtranger unto that, or knoweſt not where to have it, which ſhould give thee an entrance therein, here in this following Book, is that plainly demonſtrated, according to the holy Scriptures of Truth which ſhould give thee an entrance therein, and alſo where it is, illuſtrated by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible teſtimonies; by one who hath wandred from Mountain to Hill, to ſeek the Lord, breathing and panting after him as the chaſed Hart af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Brooks of water, but found him not until he came to wait at the true Door, which is CHRIST the LIGHT, which gives the true entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to the Scriptures of Truth, perilous times are come, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are crying, <hi>Lo her's Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>lo there's Chriſt,</hi> whereby the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-hearted <hi>(which have true hungerings &amp; thirſtings after God, and would be acquainted with the One Truth, one Faith, and one Baptiſm, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> know not which way to turn, by reaſon of the many inventions of man, and voices that are in the world, each one eſteeming hie own <hi>(his invention that he worſhippeth his God with)</hi> to be the beſt way.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the fear of God, in the cool and calm ſpirit, read over this Book, wherein thou ſhalt find many of the Principles and Doctrines of ſome of the eminenteſt Profeſſors, Paſtors and Teachers, who have a form of godlineſs, but deny the Power; the which I was an ear witneſs of; and when I heard it, I ſaid in mine heart, Great men are not alwayes wiſe in the wiſdom of God: But in the grief of my ſoul I ſaid, Men of high degree <hi>are a lye,</hi> and men of low degree <hi>are vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein alſo is an <hi>Anſwer</hi> thereunto according to the holy Scriptures of Truth, by which their folly is made manifeſt, though not with enticing words, or in the form or method of the Serpents wiſdom, unto whom it is not directed; nor for their ſakes who by his wiſdom are acted, is it written.</p>
            <p>Therefore let that noble ſpirit be in thee, as was in the
<hi>Bereans,</hi> Search the Scriptures, and compare them together, and ſee whether the things herein be true; let that of God in thee judge. The matter is great &amp; weighty which concerneth everlaſting ſalvation; And why ſhould it be thought an incredible thing, That Chriſt ſhould now be manifeſted in mortal fleſh,<pb facs="tcp:48789:3"/>qnickening them that were even dead in ſins and treſpaſſes; for verily I I have written no other thing concerning him or of the operation of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſpirit, then what in meaſure I have really (not imaginarily) ſeen and handled, and felt of his work and glory; for I dare not ſpeak of that which the Lord hath not wrought in me, and by me, or to boaſt in other mens lines; for all the world have a form of worſhip, talking of Chriſts words, and the Prophets and Apoſtles words, but are out of their Life and Power.</p>
            <p>Behold what headineſs and high-mindedneſs, treachery and betraying one another! and will be yet far worſe, by evil men and ſeducers, &amp;c. What incontinence, men and women burning in their luſts one towards another! What eating and drinking, and riſing up to play, &amp;c! and yet all covered with a Profeſſion of God and Chriſt. But how can any better fruits be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when Paſtors and Teachers tell People for Doctrines,
<hi>they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get victory over ſin on this ſide the Grave;</hi> which herein is plainly proved falſe; and the everlaſting way of Truth diſcovered, which leads out of ſin, and gives power againſt ſin on this ſide the Grave, and to live pure and holy, even as God is holy. Think it not impoſſible, with the Lord all things are poſſible.</p>
            <p>And what I have here written, is not to render any man odious, or to diſcover their nakedneſs, but for the bringing of Gods truth to Light; for I having had ſomething lying on me a long time, to give forth amongſt the Profeſſors and Baptiſts, who have any true deſires after God; and as in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the movings of the Lord, I paſſing amongſt them, ſeeing their <hi>PRACTISES,</hi> and hearing their <hi>DOCTRINES,</hi> it was now laid on me of the Lord, to give it forth as an Anſwer thereunto, which I have done for the clearing of my Conſcience in tender love, that all who love their ſouls may be warned while time is: For the diſpenſation of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time is come nigh, for the gathering together all in
<hi>ONE,</hi> even in Chriſt, whether things in Heaven, or things in Earth: The Parable of the <hi>Field</hi> is fulfilled; the <hi>Pearl</hi> is found;
<hi>Father, Mother, Husband,</hi> or <hi>Wife, Houſe</hi> or <hi>Land,</hi> all is forſaken, if the Lord calls, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even to the end of the earth, for the gathering into the unity with the Father and the Son. This is the onely deſire of him, whom the Lord hath called into his labour, which ſeeketh your Eternal good. With the meaſure of God's spirit try all things, and let not any motion paſſe away, that ſeeks truly after God, that you may come to have an infallible teſtimony of the ſpirit of the Lord <hi>in you,</hi> to lead you, and guide you: For he that believeth hath the witneſs
<hi>in himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. <hi>M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48789:3"/>
            <head>THE BAPTIST AND INDEPENDENT CHURCHES (So called) Set on Fire: By a bright ſhining Light revealed from Heaven. Their <hi>PASTORS</hi> and
<hi>TEACHERS</hi> ſcorching in the flame of it, <hi>gnaſhing</hi> and
<hi>blaſpheming</hi> God and his Tabernacle; As their Principles raſh and judging, herein record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, do demonſtrate; Which are anſwered for the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of Truth, and the ſatisfying of the ſimple. In which they are found to be children of them which killed the Juſt, and have drunken of the Cup of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, who alſo muſt drink of the Cup of Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at the hand of the Lord.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p n="1">1. <hi>EDward-Whale</hi> (accounted an
<hi>Independent</hi> Teacher, Prieſt of <hi>Waterford</hi>) affirmed—<hi>That the godlieſt man that ever was on the earth, did not get the victory over ſin, or lived free from ſin on this ſide the Grave</hi>—He did not except Chriſt. This he affirmed in his Pulpit before the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in the Idol-Temple, formerly <hi>a Maſſe-Houſe,</hi> with a Croſs on the top of it, and another at the end of it on the 21. day of the 6th. Month, 1659. in the City of
<hi>Waterford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that is born of God, doth not commit ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt the Seed of God, is in him; and as he abides in him, he cannot ſin, though he may be tempted to ſin, as<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48789:4"/>Chriſt was, yet not overcome with the temptation of ſin, but thorough Faith in Chriſt, gets the victory over ſin and temptations on this ſide the grave,
1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>ch.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. Sin is of the Devil; and he that commits it, and pleads for it, is taken captive by the Devil at his will, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5.8.</note> And for this purpoſe, Chriſt the eternal Son of God, was made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to take away ſin, and to deſtroy ſin.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14,15.</note> And foraſmuch as the children were partakers of fleſh and blood, Chriſt himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo partaked of the ſame, <hi>that thorough the death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the Devil, and deliver them, who</hi> (thorough fear) <hi>were all their life time ſubject to bondage;</hi> which Chriſt redeemed them from; for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>He was made to us wiſdom and redemption, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.50</note> And the Apoſtle did witneſs through Chriſt, victory over ſin on this ſide the grave: For ſaith he, <hi>O death! where is thy ſting? O grave, or hell! where is thy victory? The ſting of death is ſin, the ſtrength of ſin is the the Law: but</hi> (take notice) <hi>thanks be unto God which giveth us the victory thorough our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54,55,56,57. And ſo Prieſt <hi>Whale</hi> hath preached another Doctrine then Chriſt or his Miniſters, and hath (as it were) blaſphemouſly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Chriſt, his holy Prophets and Apoſtles, with ſin; for he did not except them when he ſaid,—<hi>The godlinſt man that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, did not get the victory over ſin, on this ſide the grave.</hi>—And ſo by the holy Scriptures of this truth he is corrected, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a lye in his mouth, and as it were denying the very purpoſe, work and office of God in Chriſt, which was <hi>to ſave from ſin,</hi> and <hi>(thorough
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ath)</hi> to deſtroy ſin and death, and to take it away, narling it to the croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this teſtimony I give unto all the World, for the Lord God and his truth, That it is poſſible in and thorough CHRIST JESUS <hi>the light of the world,</hi> that lighteth every one that comes into the World, that all that it love and follow in the daily Croſs, I ſay, That thorough Faith in the Blood of Chriſt (<hi>who is our example, whoſe ſteps many of us are following,</hi> (according to our meaſures) <hi>who did not ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth, &amp;c.</hi>) it is poſſible to live free from ſin, and to live a pure, righteous, and holy life, even perfect as he<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48789:4"/>is perfect in this preſent World, before this earthly Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle go down to the grave; and at this let none ſtumble, but in the cool and calm ſpirit, and in the Light and fear of God ſearch the Scriptures, for they teſtifie, that the members of the true Church, ſo lived in the days of old; and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands <hi>(bleſſed be the Lord)</hi> in this day, are living ſo, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo to live, Chriſt being the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever; (For ſaith the Apoſtle,
<hi>What manner of love hath the Father beſtowed on us, that we ſhould be called the ſons of God; therefore the world knoweth us not,</hi> (mark the reaſon) becauſe it knew him not, but ſaid, He was <hi>Joſeph's ſon, a ſinner,</hi> and <hi>hath a Devil, and deceiveth the people,</hi> Why hear ye him? Even as Teachers and Profeſſors generally cry out this day
<hi>(against his ſervants whom he hath ſent forth to bear witneſs of his true Light)</hi> that it is a natural Light, and not ſufficient to lead out of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſaith <hi>John, Beloved, now are we the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be; but we know, that when he ſhall appear,</hi> (and bleſſed be the Lord, he is appeared in his Saints, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10.) <hi>We ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is; And every one that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf</hi> (mark that) <hi>even as he is pure;</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.1.2.3. And herein was Love made perfect, and gives boldneſs in the day of Judgement, <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſay they) <hi>even as he is,</hi> (take notice of that) <hi>ſo are we in this world,</hi> 1
<hi>Joh.</hi> 4.17. He that can receive it, let him; for he was, and is without ſin, and bare our ſins in his body on the Tree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If we be dead with Chriſt, we believe that we ſhall live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>im.</hi> Now Chriſt was dead to ſin, and the Goſpel did wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s ſome of them dead to ſin, and could no longer live therein, but live unto Chriſt, in newneſs and righteouſneſs of Life; for a dead man that is really dead, cannot move, act, or ſpeak; ſo he that is really dead to ſin, cannot act or commit ſin; and <hi>Paul</hi> did ſay, That himſelf ahd others were dead to ſin, and free from ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi>
6.2.7. the old man crucified, and the body of ſin deſtroyed. Therefore, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Ver.</hi> 14.</note>
                  <hi>Reckon your ſelves to be dead indeed unto ſin, but alive unto God; thorough our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for ſin ſhall not have dominion over you; for ye are not under the Law but under Grace;</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48789:5"/>which Crace taught them to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live truly like God in this preſent world: Therefore ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.11,12.</note> 
                  <hi>Foraſmuch as Chriſt hath ſuffered for us in the fleſh, arm your ſelves likewiſe with the ſame mind, for he that hath ſuffered in the fleſh,</hi> (as Old <hi>England,</hi> and
<hi>New-England,</hi> and many other places can witneſs, how much many of the faithful ſervants of the Moſt High God have ſuffered in their fleſh, to the loſs of life, and ſpoil of Goods, for the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Jeſus, and the wicked actions on record will teſtifie to generations to come) I ſay,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hath ſuffered in the fleſh, hath ceaſed</hi> (mark) <hi>from ſin, that he no longer ſhould live to the luſt of the fleſh, or will of man, the reſt of his time, but to the will of God, &amp;c.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>God be thanked ye were</hi> (take notice, not that then they were) <hi>the ſervants of ſin, but having obeyed from the heart that form of Doctrine which was delivered you,</hi> (mark)
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>being made free from ſin, became the ſervants of Righteouſneſs.</hi> So here, according to the holy Scripture, the Apoſtle did teſtifie,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 17.</note> that the <hi>Romans (thorough the Goſpel he preached unto them)</hi> had freedom and victory over ſin on this ſide the Grave.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54.57.</note> And the Goſpel he preached, was <hi>CHRIST the LIGHT in them,</hi> and to that was he ſent to turn their minds; for, <hi>what may be known of God</hi> (he told them) <hi>was manifeſt in them, Rom.</hi> 1.19. And his Doctrine was,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4,5,6.</note> 
                  <hi>not with enticing words of mans wiſdom, but in the demonſtration of the ſpirit and power of the Lord, that their Faith might not ſtand in the wiſdom of men,</hi> (by which wiſdom they knew not God) <hi>but in the power of the Lord.</hi> Howbeit, ſaith he; <hi>We preach wiſdom
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> them that are perfect;</hi> according to Chriſt's Doctrine, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your heavenly Father is perfect:</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> was not aſhamed of this Goſpel, for it was, and is the Power of God to ſalvation, to every one that believes and follows the Light of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om.</hi> 1.16,17.</note> for therein is the righteouſneſs of God revealed from faith to faith;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oh.</hi> 5.4.</note> by which faith, the faithful came to get the victory over ſin, and freedom from ſin, and became ſervants to God, and brought forth fruits unto holineſs of life;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 6.22,23.</note> the end of which was, and is, everlaſting peace;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atth.</hi> 25.46.</note> but the wages of ſin living and dying in it, is everlaſting death, and puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48789:5"/>Obj. <hi>But did not Paul ſay, O wretched man!</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And ſo</hi> (though a man may ſay, ſome be freed from the guilt of ſin: yet <hi>it cannot be, that men may be free from the acting or committing of ſin, whilſt they are on earth, &amp;c. but by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to them, they ſhall he ſaved that believe in Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> He that acteth or committeth ſin, is under the guilt and condemnation for ſin; for he that commits ſin is of the Devil, and the Light wil be his condemnation; <hi>and whoſoever abides in him</hi> (ſaith John,) <hi>ſinneth not, whoſoever ſinneth, hath not ſeen him, neither knoweth him;</hi> for he dyed for ſinners and ungodly ones, but not to live in ſin, but unto himſelf, which dyed for them, 2 Cor:
5: 15 and the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, imputed to any that live in ſin, and daily act and commit ſin, that will ſtand them in little ſtead, in the day of the Lords account, when he ſhall give to every one according to the deeds done in the body: And although the Scripture ſaith; <hi>Abraham believed God, and it was imputed unto him for righteouſneſs;</hi> yet it doth not ſay, that the righteouſneſs of Chriſt ſhall be imputed to them, which daily live and abide in ſin. <hi>Abraham</hi> believed, and alſo obeyed the command of God; now that which was written, concerning
<hi>Abrahams</hi> righteouſneſs that was imputed unto him, was not written for his ſake alone, as ſaith the Scripture, but for us alſo to whom
<hi>(take notice of that)</hi> it ſhall be imputed, if we believe; <hi>(mark and take notice)</hi> if ye believe, it ſhall be imputed unto you for righteouſneſs; if ye ſay, ye do believe, then ye ſhall not abide in ſin; if ye believe and follow the Light of Chriſt in you, then you ſhall not <hi>(ſaith Chriſt)</hi> abide in darkneſs, ſin, or evil, but ſhall have the Light of Life. Compare <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>John</hi>
12.46. to <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.23,24,25. And as for <hi>Paul's</hi> ſaying, <hi>O wretched man!</hi> &amp;c. I do affirme in the fear of God, according to what I have received of the Lord, and ſhall make it to appeare, by the aforegoing words of the Apoſtle to the Romans, and alſo by the words following, that it was not the Apoſtles then preſent condition, when he ſaid, <hi>O wretched man that I am! &amp;c.</hi> but a condition that he had once paſſed through, which through Chriſt, he did witneſs a freedom from
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8,12: onely it was the manner of the Prophets and Apoſtles when they writ to the people, and for the condeſcending to the low eſtate or condition,<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48789:6"/>that thoſe they writ unto were in, to rank themſelves with them, to wit, in uſing the word <hi>We,</hi> or
<hi>Us;</hi> as for inſtance, <hi>if we ſay, we have noſin, or have not ſinned &amp;c. And in mamy things we offend all;</hi> And as Iſaiah ſaith, <hi>Lord why haſt thou cauſed us to erre from thy wayes. James.</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 36.17. But
<hi>Paul,</hi> as is a fore ſhewed, affirmed, <hi>they were really dead to ſin Rom.</hi> 6.2. and he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth an infallible reaſon for it; for ſaith he, <hi>Know ye not, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us, as were baptized into Chriſt, were baptized into his death,</hi> that like as Chriſt was raiſed from the grave, ſo they were to walk in newneſs of life <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. to the 8. and ſo they came from under the dominion of ſin, and from under the Condemnation of the Law. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.15 <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.1. but whiles a man lives, the Law hath Power over him: He that hath an ear to hear, can hear and underſtand;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14</note> but he over whom, and in whom death reigns, though he may talk of Chriſt and his righteouſneſs, of Faith and Grace &amp;c. yet not being turned to the Light, which is the Law;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.13,14.</note> he is not come ſo far as the pure law of God, neither knowes he it in righteouſneſs and truth, but is a ſtranger unto it; for ſaith <hi>Paul, Know ye not, my brethren how that the Law hath dominion over a man ſo long as he liveth; for I ſpeake to them,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>that know the Law, for the woman that hath an husband, is bound by the Law to her huſband, ſo long as he liveth; but if her huſband be dead, ſhe is loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the Law of her huſband: ſo that ſhe is no adultereſs, thoughſhe be marryed to another.</hi> Wherefore ſaith he, <hi>my brethren, ye alſo are</hi> (not that ye ſhall) <hi>become dead to the Law, by the body of Chriſt, that ye ſhould be marryed to another, even to Chriſt who is raiſed from the dead thorough whom they brought forth fruits unto God;</hi> for ſaith he, when they were in the fleſh, (he did not then ſay they now are in the fleſh, or following the motions of the fleſh) the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſin which were by the Law, wrought in their members ſin, and brought ſorth fruits unto death; but now he ſaid, they were delivered from the Law, that they ſhould ſerve in newneſs of ſpirit;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall we ſay then,</hi> (ſaith he)
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Is the Law ſin? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid; for he had not-known ſin, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not covet. But ſin taking occaſion by the Commandement, wrought in him all manner of Concupiſcente. For he was alive</hi> (mark and take notice of that) <hi>ONCE.</hi> He there told them what he was once, but by the receiving of the Law, which cauſed ſin to abound<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48789:6"/>and appear exceeding ſinful, he cried out, <hi>O wretched man! &amp;c.</hi> So there was a time <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw his ſin to abound by the Law, &amp;c. and there was a time he did witneſs he was dead to ſin; And there was a time he told them, <hi>The Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, had freed him from the Law of Sin and Death:</hi> And that was <hi>Paul's</hi> then preſent condition; for ſaith he, <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh, or its motions; for they that ſo do, cannot pleaſe God;</hi> But ſaith he,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, <hi>to</hi> 10.</note>
                  <hi>Ye are not in the ſteſh, but in the Spirit, if the Spirit of God dwelleth in you. Now if any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his:</hi> he gives a character of them that have this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whereby in the Light of the Son of God they may judg and examine themſelves; for if the Spirit of Chriſt be in thee, the body is dead, becauſe of ſin; but the Spirit is Life, becauſe of Righteouſneſs: So that through this Spirit of Life, <hi>Paul</hi> did witneſs a freedom from ſin, and a Victory over ſin, on this ſide the grave, and thanked God for it, and ſaid, <hi>He had fought the good ſight, he had finiſhed his courſe, he had kept the Faith,</hi> which gave victory over the world, or ſin, <hi>and henceforth</hi> (ſaith he)
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 7 8,9.</note> 
                  <hi>there is laid up for me a Crown of Glory and Righteouſneſs, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day; and not onely to me, but unto all them which love his appearance.</hi> And although <hi>Paul</hi> did cry out of the thorn in the fleſh, and of the buffeting of Satan, leſt he ſhould be exalted above his meaſure;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11,12.</note> the Lord did not impute that unto him, as ſin, but ſaid, <hi>My grace is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for thee;</hi> which Grace taught <hi>Paul</hi> and the Saints to deny ſin, and ungodlineſs; whereby they lived like God in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world.</p>
               <p>So that it is evident by the Scriptures of Truth, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Saints in Light did witneſs a redemption from ſin, and were regenerated, waſhed and cleanſed, and ſanctified on this ſide the grave. Read and compare theſe Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Rom.</hi>
6.2.7.22. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. <hi>to</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
6.11. <hi>Ch.</hi> 15.55,56,57. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7,8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
4.1,2.</p>
               <p>So I being caſt into Priſon, that very day that <hi>Prieſt Whale</hi> thus affirmed, not giving any juſt offence in word or action; as
<hi>Prieſt Whale</hi> paſſed by the Priſon, I required him to prove where man ſhould be made free from ſin? ſeeing that he had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48789:7"/>affirmed—<hi>That the godlieſt man that ever was, did not get the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over ſin, on this ſide the grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Anſwer was—<hi>They ſhould be cleanſed in heaven.</hi>—O wretched man! How haſt thou darkned the Counſel of the moſt High God? uttering words without the true knowledg of God, from thy wiſdom, which is from beneath; which is earthly, ſenſual and bruitiſh; and how haſt thou deceived thouſands of ſouls <hi>(Wo is me for thee! the Controverſie of the Lord will be great with thee and you all)</hi> and have taken their moneys for that which is not Bread, and have made them ſpend their labour all the daies of their lives, for that which doth not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit their immortal ſouls, which wil be required at thine, &amp; ſuch blind guides hands, as thou art. May not the People &amp; State, <hi>wch</hi> have given thee a great houſe &amp; 150 <abbr>l.</abbr> a year (<hi>ſome ſay</hi> 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>a year</hi>) truly ſay, <hi>It is for nought?</hi> for if people can never be made free from ſin, or get the victory over ſin, on this ſide the grave <hi>(the contrary I have proved by the Scripture of Truth)</hi> is it not then plainly made manifeſt, that thou haſt taken the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mony for nought, and deceived them, and ſo haſt clothed thy ſelf with the fine of the wooll (<hi>and thy wife her garments la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with ſilver and gold, from the neck down to the foot</hi> (the poor ready to periſh with hunger and nakedneſs)
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
2.9,10.</note> 
                  <hi>lace upon lace, ſome near as broad as four fingers, which is not according to the ornaments of the holy women of old, which were not laced with ſilver or gold, or plaiting of the hair, but covered with the ornament of a meek and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſpirit, which in the ſight of God is of great price</hi>) and haſt fed thy ſelf with the fat; and neither thou, nor any of you all have fed the poor and needy, nor bound up that which is broken, nor healed at the bottom that which was ſick, nor brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain that which was driven away, but with fierce wrath and cruelty have ye ruled. And now to cover thy wickedneſs and deceit, thou <hi>Prieſt Whale</hi> ſayeſt, <hi>They muſt be cleanſed from ſin in Heaven,</hi> which is alſo contrary to the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>No unclean thing, Idolaters, nor Adulterers, effeminate perſons, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankind, nor covetous perſons, nor drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, or any that defiles, or works abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or that makes a lye, ſhall inherit the kingdom of God, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into that holy City; and as the tree falls, ſo it lies,</hi> Eccl.
1.3. 1 Cor.<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48789:7"/>6.9 Rev. 21.27. But ſaith <hi>Paul, ſuch were</hi> (take notice) <hi>ſome of you;</hi> But they came to be waſhed, cleanſed, and ſanctified <hi>by the name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and
<hi>by the Spirit of their God,</hi> before ever they entered God's Kingdom; which is joy, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and peace in the Holy Ghoſt, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. to the 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. And now let that of God in you all judge, Whether that Doctrine <hi>Prieſt Whale</hi> preached, be according to the Scriptures; and all people beware of them; to wit, ſuch Teachers as <hi>Priest Whale,</hi> and come out from amongſt them, leſt ye partake of their plagues, and conſider your paths and ponder your waies, and what you have benefitted in the things of God, by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and learning of ſuch Teachers, and ceaſe from them, and mind that of God <hi>in you;</hi> and as you come to mind and obey that, it will lead you unto God the Father of Life, and open your underſtandings, and as you come to wait on the Lord, it will reveal the true knowledge and glory of God <hi>in you,</hi> in the face of Jeſus Chriſt; the key of which your Teachers have taken from you, and cauſed you to err from the right way of the Lord, even <hi>CHRIST</hi> the
<hi>LIGHT;</hi> who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>2. The Principles and judging of <hi>Robert Car</hi> Baptiſt, Paſtor in <hi>Clonmell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>He affirmed the 10<hi>th.</hi> day of the 5<hi>th</hi> month,
1659,—<hi>That the Scripture was the Rule of Life and Faith to Salvation; And that the Scripture was the more ſure word of Prophecie, that Peter ſpake of, and the Law &amp; Teſtimony</hi>—And for us, that are called Quakes, to affirm, <hi>that the Spirit of truth from God received, was the true rule of life to ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. he ſaid—<hi>It was a fiction of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The true and everlaſting Rule of life to Salvation, and the Author of Faith, which is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the holy Scripture is a true declaration of, which is Chriſt the Eternal ſon of God, the Spirit of life and truth, which lighteth every one that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13.</note> which whoſoever loves, and followes the Light of the ſon of God, comes to receive, the Spirit of Life and truth, which leades into all truth, and the Light and Spirit of truth, is the Law, and<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48789:8"/>Teſtimony, which was before the writings of <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.26.</note> 
                  <hi>To the Law, and to the Teſtimony.</hi> Now when <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpake thoſe words, the Evangeliſts writings were not writen;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.
<hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Prov.</hi> 6 23</note> therefore the Law and Teſtimony is another thing, and <hi>within man;</hi> for ſaith God, <hi>I wil make an everlaſting Covenant with the houſe of I ſrael, I wil put my Law and fear in their hearts, and write it in their inward parts.</hi> Now the
<hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Light,</hi> which they that believe in, &amp; follow, come to receive the ſpirit of Life and truth, as I ſaid before, and that is the Teſtimony of Jeſus; <hi>for the Teſtimony of Jeſus</hi> (ſaith
<hi>John,</hi>) <hi>is the ſpirit of Propheſie</hi> Rev. 19.10. And this Spirit the Apoſtle did witneſs was come amongſt them, and bare witneſs to their Spirits, that they were the ſons of God; for ſaith he,
<hi>becauſe ye are ſonnes, God hath given forth the Spirit of his Son into your</hi> (take notice) <hi>hearts,</hi> Gal. 4 6. And by this Spirit and Light, they came to be led out of the luſts of the fleſh, and through the Croſs of Chriſt knew a cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of it; and that life in them, that ſtood in outwards ſignes and things that periſhed in the uſing, which
<hi>Paul</hi> gloried not in, neither deſired to glory in any thing, ſave the Croſs of Chriſt; for he knew, and ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15.</note>
                  <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> though it was in its time ſerviceable, and commanded of the Lord, yet it availed them nothing; yea, he told them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If they were Circumciſed, Chriſt would profit them nothing.</hi> But the new was to be accepted, which was the onely work of the Spirit of the Lord, through its eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal working and operation in their hearts, circumciſing of it, and cleanſing of it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6.</note> whereby they who abides its working, comes to receive the faith of God's Elect, which works by love, into the obedience to the Spirit of Truth, and the ſure word of Prophecie, which is nigh them, even in their hearts and mouths; which divideth the evil motions, and the evil words, from the good, and gives power againſt them, as they do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; whereby all that come to obey and take heed unto that more ſure Word, come to know their ſanctification, and ſo the New Creature they come to know, and the Mercy and Peace of God comes to be muſtiplied in them, and on them walking according to that Rule. And
<hi>Peter</hi> did not ſay, the Writings of the Evangeliſts were that more ſure Word, than that they heard in the Mount, which was the living Word of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48789:8"/>the Lord that abides for ever, which by the Goſpel was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto them; and of this Living Word muſt all be born that ever come to know ſalvation; which <hi>Word is in the heart, and is quick and powerful, and ſharper than any two-edged ſword; even to the dividing of the joints and marrow, ſoul and ſpirit, and the thoughts and intents of the heart:</hi> And this <hi>WORD David</hi> ſaid <hi>hee had hid in his heart, out of which came the Iſſues of life.</hi> So <hi>Peter</hi> told them of another Word than the Words heard in the Mount: Read and compare theſe Scriptures: The ſpiritual man compares ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23,24,25. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17, to 21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1.
<hi>Rev.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 6,7,8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. So they which put the Letter which killeth, for the Rule of Life and Faith unto Salvation, in ſtead of the Spirit which quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, are in the (<hi>if I may ſpeak</hi> Robert Carrs <hi>words</hi>) fictions of the Divel, and out of the true Faith and Truth of Jeſus, and not guided by that holy Spirit which righteous
<hi>Abel, Enoch</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> were, before the Scriptures were written, and ſhall be for ever, when Scripture ſhall be no more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>3. The Principles of <hi>Edward Whale,</hi> Priest of
<hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and Prieſt <hi>Millard</hi> of <hi>Paſſage</hi> near
<hi>Waterford.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Each of them affirmed in the Pulpit, in the Idol Temple of Waterford,—<hi>That that Light, which we</hi> (called Quakers) <hi>bear teſtimony unto, which Chriſt hath enlightened every man withall that comes into the world, they ſay</hi> (ſay the Prieſts) <hi>they have a Light within them, but how great is that darkneſs.</hi> This they both affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here ye Prieſts have brought your ſelvs under the <hi>WOE,</hi> which call the true <hi>LIGHT</hi> which lighteth every one that cometh into the world, <hi>great darkneſs;</hi> for <hi>WO</hi> is to them <hi>that call Light darkneſs, &amp; darkneſs Light,</hi> Iſa.
5.20. <hi>for I am the Light of the world,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, and he bids them walk in the Light, <hi>he that walketh in the Light, ſtumbles not; but he that walketh in the dark ſtumbles, and knowes not where he goes, becauſe there is no Light in him;</hi> for the Light of the wicked, which rebel againſt the Light, ſhall be put out. <hi>I am come a Light into the world,</hi> ſaith Chaiſt, <hi>and he bids them walk in the Light; for he that believes in the Light, and<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48789:9"/>followes it, ſhall not walk or abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 8 12,</note> and no other Light than Chriſt, do we teſtify of, which God ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.9.</note> 
                  <hi>he would give for a Light, to lighten the Gentiles, and for a Covenant to the people, and for ſalvation to the ends of the earth.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> a true Miniſter of God,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18</note> was ſent <hi>to turn from darkneſs to the Light, and from Satan's power to the living God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18 19.</note> And he told them
<hi>what might be known of God, was manifeſt in them,</hi> And <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaid, <hi>if the wicked confeſs their ſin, God will deliver their ſoul from going down to the pit, and their life ſhall ſee the Light, and be enlightned again with the Light of the living, Jo.</hi> 12.46. <hi>Job</hi>
18.5. <hi>cha.</hi> 24. <hi>chap.</hi> 23.26. to the 31. And <hi>John,</hi> a man ſent of God, came to bear teſtimony of the Light, and ſaid, <hi>That was the true Light that lighted every one that comes into the world, Jo.</hi>
1.9, So ye Prieſts, and ye all, who deny the Light, that lighteth every one that comes into the world, are found to preach another do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine than Chriſt and his Apoſtles preached, and ſo are not to be received into the houſe, neither bid God ſpeed, for they that ſo do, will partake of your plagues, 2
<hi>Jo.</hi> 9,10,11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>4. The Principles and Judgement of Captain <hi>Samuel Wade</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſt Teacher, given under his hand, as followeth.</head>
               <p>—<hi>I do believe thoſe people called Quakers are under the higheſt deluſion in the world, &amp;c. in the magnifying the Light within, and ſtands in oppoſition to Chriſt without and the Scriptures. And the firſt riſe of the Quakers was in</hi> London <hi>about the year</hi> 1647, as witneſs <hi>S. Wade.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is agreeable, and according to the Scriptures, to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and exalt <hi>God</hi> in <hi>man,</hi> and the Spirit in <hi>man,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt the Light in man;</hi> for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>What may be known of God (who is Light) is manifeſt in man, Rom.</hi> 1.18. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.5. And Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I am the Light, which is within, except ye be reprobates, and this Light ſhined in the dark heart of man, but the darkneſs compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended it not;</hi> but the Lord now by his eternall power hath cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>commanded the Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, and hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> (take notice) <hi>in our hearts; and hath given the true knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>chap.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.1.
<hi>to</hi> 9. And the Scripture ſaith, <hi>If any man have not the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48789:9"/>Spirit of Chriſt in him, he is none of his; but if the Spirit of Chriſt be in you, the body is dead, and the Spirit is life becauſe of righte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſneſs.</hi> And this teſtimony I give for the Lord, and his truth, that the ſame Spirit of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> that raiſed Jeſus from the grave,
<hi>is in us;</hi> and by it hath God quickened, and is quickning our mortall fleſh, even by his Spirit, that dwelleth <hi>in us;</hi> which is that myſtery that hath been h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſince the long night of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, theſe many generations, <hi>even Chriſt in us the hope of Glory, Col.</hi> 1.25,26,27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi>
9.10.11. and God is a Spirit, and all that ever come to worſhip God in truth, muſt worſhip him with, and in the Spirit of truth: And therefore let that of God in all Judge, whether it be deluſion to be led and guided by the Spirit of truth, or in oppoſition againſt Chriſt and the Scriptures, to extol and magnifie the Light, or Spirit within, for ſaith Chriſt, when he was with his Diſciples, <hi>if I go not away, the Comforter will not come; but If I go away, I will ſend you the Comforter, even the Spirit of truth, which ſhall lead you and guide you into all truth.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto the <hi>Galatians, becauſe ye are ſons, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his ſon</hi> (take notice) <hi>into your hearts, &amp;c.</hi> Jo. 16 13. Gal. 4.6.</p>
               <p>And therefore thou <hi>Samuel Wade,</hi> and all you Profeſſors of the world, that talk of Chriſt in your fleſhly wiſedom, which is from beneath, and is ſenſuall and brutiſh, your knowledge muſt periſh, and dye, if ever the true Comſorter, the Spirit of life and truth from God ye come to know, or enjoy; for that is but a knowing Chriſt in the fleſh, or fleſh glorying in Chriſt, but an enmity to the Croſs of Chriſt; and I can truly ſay, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>though I have known Chriſt in the fleſh, yet henceforth I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know him ſo no more.</hi> To Gods witneſs <hi>in you all</hi> I ſpeak, which did never change or conſent to ſin, unto which, as your mindes come to be turned, and by it to be lead and guided, it will cauſe you to ceaſe from your own words, and to know the time to keep ſilent; for a time of ſilence <hi>(if ever ye come to miniſter from the Spirit of truth)</hi> ſhall ye Baptiſts
<hi>(will ye, nill ye)</hi> and all Profeſſors on the face of the earth, come to know;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> and ſo as in the meaſure of Gods Spirit, (which is given to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you, to profit withall,) ye come to wait, in the pure fear of the Lord, that will be a bridle to your tongue; and a<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48789:10"/>limit to your airy Spirit, and ſo as your minds come to be ſtaid in the meaſure of Gods Spirit, and receive a word by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of the Almighty, to declare, for the edifying or build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the members of that body, of which Chriſt is the head, according as you receive <hi>(mark, it muſt be your own, and onely your own &amp; not an others)</hi> So ye are to miniſter as good ſtewards of the manifold gifts and graces of God; and then let him be accurſed that ſhould it ſeek to quench; For if one had the tongues of men and Angels, and could ſpeak all the myſteries of Kingdome of God, in that mind which is not guided by the Spirit of Truth, not in the life of truth, that is but death and hell, talking of the ſame of wiſedom, but a ſtranger, as to the enjoying of the thing, and muſt be ſilent, and peradventure death reigning over him, and not come ſo far, as to the receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the righteous Law of God, where the Thunders Voices and Earthquakes are felt, ſeen and heard, <hi>for ſo dreadfull was thy preſence</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>that I exceedingly quake and tremble,</hi> for where the Law is not received within, death reigns and hath dominion, and the day not yet known that makes the ſtrong man <hi>to bow,</hi> and the keepers of the houſe <hi>to tremble; For I came not to deſtroy the Law</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>but to fulfill it, and Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, but not one jot or one tittle of the Law ſhall paſs away till all be fulfilled;</hi> So all come to the <hi>Light</hi> and follow the <hi>Light,</hi> which to the life will lead, the Law for to fulfill;
<hi>The Law</hi> is <hi>Light</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to do thy will O God</hi> (mark) <hi>thy Law is in my heart, and the mouth of the righteous ſpeaketh wiſedom, his tongue talketh of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Law of his God is in his heart,</hi> Pſal. 37.30,31. Pſal. 40 8. Prov. 6.23. and Chriſt ſaid <hi>I in them and thou in me; that they all may be made perfect in one,</hi> Jo 17.22,23. chap 16.13. <hi>and he that believeth on the Son of God</hi> (1 Jo. 5.10.) <hi>hath the witneſs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> And when <hi>John</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> wrote to the Churches, concerning the ſeducers, that would have ſeduced them from the anoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God <hi>within them;</hi> they told them, <hi>there were falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets amongſt the people; as there ſhould be alſo amongſt them, who privily ſhould bring in damnable hereſies</hi> (take notice ye that deny the Light and Spirit within) <hi>even denying the Lord that bought them; and many ſhall follow their pernicious ways; by reaſon of whom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48789:10"/>the way of truth ſhall be evil Spoken of</hi> (I am the
<hi>Way</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> ſaith Chriſt) ſuch were and are they that have mens perſons in admiration, becauſe of advantage, without naturall affection; filthy dreamers which defile the fleſh; ſpeaking evill of dignities, &amp; deſpiſe dominion, the higher power Chriſt the power of God, unto whomall power in heaven &amp; earth is given; who have eyes ful of adultery, pleading animpoſſibility of being made free from ſin on this ſide the grave; living in pride and vanity, lovivg plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, eating and drinking, and riſing to play; for which God ſlew twenty three thouſand in one day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. and found in <hi>Cains</hi> way, <hi>Core</hi> and
<hi>Balaams</hi> way, loving the wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and cringing and bowing according to the faſhions of the world, which muſt paſs away; and worſhiping and ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Creature more than the Cteator, <hi>Who is God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Now in the Light of the ſon of God, Examine your ſelves ye Baptiſts whether you are not guilty of theſe ſins; and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſgreſſing the doctrine and commands of Chriſt, calling men maſter; and are called maſter; and ſwearing and pleading for it; and ſeeking the favour and friendſhip of the world; which is enmity againſt God, and taking thought what to eat, or what to drink, and what to put on, read <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23. What then are you baptized unto? And whereas ſome of you ſay—<hi>That every one is not inlightned with ſaving Light,</hi>—Do you think it would ſtand with the juſtice of the Almighty; <hi>ſeeing the Scripture hath concluded, and teſtiſteth, That all men have ſinned</hi>) for to ſave ſome in ſin, and condemne others in ſin? I tell you nay: therefore let every mouth (which would ſo ſay) be ſtopt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the impartiall God, for he would not that any ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: for as all have ſinned and come ſhort of obedience: to the ſpirit and grace of God, in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in the fall; the Lord is therefore calling all men every where to repentance: and hath called ſome to repentance not to be repented of; and hath given to every man a meaſure of his Spirit, Light and Grace though it is not yet made manifeſt or known to every man; and for the time of ignorance God winked; and hath now ſent forth, and is ſending his faithfull meſſengers <hi>(which love not their lives to the death)</hi> to the four quarters of the earth, to preach his everlaſting Goſpell: and repentance, and remiſſion of ſins, through faith in the blood<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48789:11"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, and to turn mens minds from vanities, and dumb idols, to the Light of the living, which he hath enlightned them withall: he that believes and receives their teſtimony which is Chriſt the truth, and it follows, ſhall be ſaved; but he that receives not, nor obeys, ſhal be condemned; the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, and this will be the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the world: to wit, <hi>the Light in man:</hi> which ſhews him his evill deeds, of which the impartial God <hi>(as I ſaid before)</hi> a meaſure hath given to every man on the face of the whole earth, whom he would have to be ſaved, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and obedience of the truth; this the witneſs of God in all conſciences ſhal witneſs to be true: Diſobedience and Unbelief in Chriſt the Light within will be the cauſe of deſtruction to all that periſh.</p>
               <p>Neither do we <hi>(as ſome imagine)</hi> put creatures on works and duties, according to the firſt Covenant, for life and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The Law indeed ſaith, <hi>do this and live:</hi> but it is one thing to work for life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and another thing to work or act in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the life and power of God received: For God hath firſt given a meaſure of his Spirit unto man before he requires ought of him, and ſo his work is before him, and his reward is with him: even the preſence of the Lord of Life; which makes glad the hearts of the upright which follow him in the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: For ſaith <hi>David, in the day of thy power thy people ſhall be a willing people;</hi> So in the Light which from the life of Chriſt doth come, and up to the life of Chriſt it leads all that follow it:
<hi>Is the power in man,</hi> but not of man. It is the gift of God: unto it is man required to be obedient: and what ever the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of man, is a Croſs to man in the fall, and contrary to the will of man: So that I ſay and affirm in the fear of God: we do not put any on works, or duries, according to the firſt Covenant; for life and ſalvation: for by the deeds of the Law no fleſh ſhall be juſtified. But a meaſure of Gods Light, Grace, and Spirit of truth being firſt given freely to every man: to it obedience is required, which as I ſaid before, is a Croſs to the will of man: through which Croſs is the power of God felt to the ſlaying of the enmity, and the cleanſing of the heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the faith of Gods Elect comes to be received, which works by love in obedience to what the Lord requires; and ſo by the<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48789:11"/>ſame power as Chriſt was raiſed from the grave, comes the Creature to be quickened, even his mortall body, by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, that dwells <hi>in him;</hi> and ſo comes to be changed to walk in newneſs of Life: through obedience to the Life of God <hi>in man,</hi> for Chriſt himſelf learned obedience in the days when he was manifeſt in fleſh, and being made perfect through ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, became the author of eternall ſalvation to all them that obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8,9 and ſo to preſs the Creature to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Light and Spirit of Life and Truth within, it is not againſt Chriſt, nor contrary to the Scripture, nor a ſetting man to work for Life: but to work in obedience to the Life received, is according to the doctrine of Chriſt: and is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the ground work of ſalvation.</p>
               <p>But I muſt once more return to my preſent work, to wit to the magnifying of the Light and anointing within: for ſaith <hi>John,</hi> when he writ to the Saints, concerning thoſe which would have ſeduced them from the Light and anointing he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to abide in that of God in them; for ſaith he, <hi>I have not writ unto you, becauſe ye know not the truth; but becauſe ye have known it that ye might abide in it; Let that therefore abide</hi> (mark) <hi>in you, which ye have heard from the beginning, If that which ye have heard from the beginning</hi> (take notice) <hi>ſhall remain in you, ye alſo ſhall continue in the Father and in the Son: and the anointing which ye have received of him</hi> (mark that) <hi>abides in you: and ye need not that any ſhould teach you; but as the ſame anoynting teacheth you of all things, and is truth and is no lye, and as it hath taught you ye ſhall abide in him,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.21. <hi>to</hi> 27. and ſo to magnifie the Light and Spirit within, and walk in obedience to it, is not Spirituall deluſion nor againſt Chriſt, nor in oppoſition to the Scripture which is largely proved by the Scriptures of truth: But they that are not guided by the Light and Spirit of truth within, are in the Spirituall deluſion. And whereas thou <hi>S. W.</hi> ſpeaks—of <hi>magnifying the Light within againſt Chriſt and in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Scriptures of truth—Paul</hi> ſaith, when he writ to the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians, I would ye ſhould underſtand, Brethren, that the things which have hapened unto me; have fallen out rather to the furtherance of the Goſpel, ſo that my bonds in Chriſt are manifeſt, &amp;c. for I know that it ſhall turn to my ſalvation, through your prayers: and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48789:12"/>of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt. according to my expectation and my hope, that in nothing I ſhall be aſhamed: but that with all boldneſs as always</hi> (take notice of that) <hi>ſo now alſo, Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body, &amp;c.</hi> And there is not any one thing in all the whole Scripture more clear to be proved, then the magnifying of Chriſt, the Law, Light, and Spirit of Truth <hi>in man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the firſt Riſe of us <hi>(which ſcorners call Quakers)</hi> which <hi>S. W.</hi> ſaith—<hi>was in London about the year</hi> 47—it is no more true; then his charging of us—<hi>that the magnifying of the Light within, ſtands in oppoſition to Chriſt and the Scripture</hi>—: But as for the eternall power of the Lord God of hoſts; which in righteouſneſs hath been revealed, and made manifeſt amongſt us: more then hath been of late ages, through the long night of Apoſtacy; by which proud fleſh hath exceedingly quaked and trembled, that was not firſt in <hi>London</hi> (as <hi>S.W. dreameth</hi>) but in the North of <hi>England;</hi> as many faithful witneſſes can teſtifie if required; and the firſt that ever was known to give us that name of <hi>Quakers (as I heard out of the mouth of a true &amp; faithfull witneſs of the Lord)</hi> was a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Juſtice, in <hi>Darby Shire, Gervas Bennet;</hi> (as I remember) <hi>about the year</hi> 1652. yet the power of the Lord was witneſſed, before that time, amongſt our friends in the North. Yet that was not the firſt riſe of the <hi>Quakers</hi> or <hi>Quaking</hi> which
<hi>S. W.</hi> ſaith <hi>was in London,</hi> which plainly manifeſteth to all the Children of Light; that Captain <hi>Wade</hi> is no Miniſter of Chriſt? neither following him in the regeneration: for they that follow Chriſt, in their mouths is found no guile <hi>(mark that)</hi> neither do they ſpeak a lye, for quaking was thouſands of years before that: For ſaith <hi>Moſes, ſo dreadfull was thy preſence that I did exceedingly quake and tremble, Heb.</hi> 12.21 And <hi>Iſaac, which was before Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hundreds</hi> (if not thouſands) <hi>of years,</hi> did witneſs quaking or trembling; for when he heard the voice of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Hunter; he exceedingly trembled, <hi>Gen</hi> 27.33. And in the holy war, in the days of old, the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Gariſon; and the ſpoylers
<hi>(mark ye ſpoylers, who make a prey and ſpoyl of the Lords ſervants, and their outward ſubſtance, a Day of horror and perplexity is coming on you)</hi> and the ſpoylers alſo did <hi>quake</hi> and <hi>tremble;</hi> and there was a great <hi>trembling</hi> and <hi>quaking</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48789:12"/>in the Hoſt in the field, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.15. And
<hi>David</hi> ſaid <hi>his fleſh did tremble, he was afraid of the judgements of the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 119.120. And <hi>Daniel</hi> that holy Prophet, when he ſaw the Viſion, and heard the voice of the Lord,
<hi>ſtood trembling, and a great qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fell on them that ſtood by, Dan,</hi> 10.7, to the 11. And <hi>Hab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakuck</hi> when he heard the Decree of the Lord, againſt the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who built towns with blood, and eſtabliſhed Cities by ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and that gave drink to their neighbours, till they were drunken and their nakedneſs ſeen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and violence was done on mens blood: and they taught lyes, and truſted in dumb Idols <hi>(take notice)</hi> and their rejoicing was to devour the poor ſecretly: for the which the man of God ſaw the Lord would be avenged of them, in the day he would invade them with his troops <hi>(or compaſs them about with his terrible army with diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed banners)</hi> the which when the Prophet heard, <hi>his belly trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and his lips quivered, rottenneſs entred into his bowel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> he trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that he might reſt; in that day of trouble, <hi>ſuch a man</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi>)
<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.2, to the 5.</note> 
                  <hi>hath the Lord regard unto: which is of meek and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit, that trembles at his Word, Habak.</hi> 2.8. to the end <hi>chap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>See thou S. <hi>W.</hi> and you all that deſpiſes
<hi>quaking</hi> do plainly manifeſt you are not come to the opening of the Book in which the myſtery of God have been ſealed, &amp; hid from the Vultrous eye, &amp;c. And <hi>I beheld</hi> (ſaith <hi>John</hi>) <hi>when he had opened the ſixth ſeal, and lo there was a great Earthquake</hi> (<hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12) but thou muſt come to know; the pouring out of the vialls, by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Angels, which is pouring forth, the wrath of God on the earth, as you may read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. the whole world that lyes in wickedneſs ſhall feel what is contained in that Chapter: much there lies in it, which I am not permited to ſpeak; <hi>And when the ſeventh Angell poured forth</hi> (mark ye airy Spirits) <hi>his viall into the air, and there came a great voyce out of the Temple ſaying, it is done,</hi> and <hi>there were Voyces and Thunders, and Lightnings; and there was a great Earthquake, ſuch as was not ſince men were on the earth: ſo mighty an earthquake: and ſo great,</hi> Rev. 16.17. This hath been truly witneſſed, and is witneſſing amongſt thoſe whom the Lord hath redeemed and is redeeming:
<hi>For the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah hath roared out of Sion; who wil not fear? And the Lord hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſie?</hi> his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48789:13"/>power is made manifeſt and his glory is revealing, and he will overturn, overturn, overturn, till he come to raign whoſe right it is: <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the <hi>King.</hi> of
<hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords.</hi> the onely Potentate of heaven and earth, and he <hi>in man</hi> ſhall rule and reign over all the world in righteouſneſs: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by true judgement ſhall be ſet up in the earth, and executed on all tranſgreſſors without reſpect of Perſons; for he will rule the Heathen with a rod of Iron: and all that gather againſt his choſen ones, ſhall be broken in pieces like a potters veſſell, and no weapon formed againſt them ſhall proſper, and every tongue that riſeth againſt them ſhall be condemned; for in Chriſt our righteouſneſs are we eſtabliſhed and eſtabliſhing: And he that rides on the white horſe, is goneforth Conquering and to Conquer; and with the rod of his lips will he ſmite and is ſmiting the earth; and with the Spirit of his mouth, and bright glorious appearance is conſuming the Spirit of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and the pride and glory of all fleſh he is marring and ſtaining; for Chriſt is come in his ten thouſands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For ſo I have read it: in an old <hi>Arrianiſh Teſtament</hi> I ſaw in
<hi>Clonmell:</hi> in theſe very expreſs words as followeth, and of theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying,
<hi>behold our Lord is come in his holy thouſands to do judgement againſt all, and to reprove all the impious, of all the works of their impiety, whereby they have done impiouſly; and of all the hard things which impious ſinners have ſpoken againſt him,</hi> Jude 41.15.</p>
               <p>Therefore Awake, awake, ye that are reſting in forms, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power, feeding on the husk, the letter which killeth, and are covered, but not with the Spirit of the Lord, The all ſeeing eye is opened before whom the ſecrets, and intents of all hearts are naked and bare; your bed is to ſhort, and your covering will not hide you: you are weighed in an equall ballance, and comprehended as half a ſpan, by him who hath meaſured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with a ſpan, and weighed the mountains in ſcales: and the hills in a ballance, from which in vain is ſalvation hoped. Therefore Ariſe, Ariſe, ye Baptiſts, that is not your true reſt ye now are in, it is polluted, and will be your great deſtruction, except ye ſpeedily repent, for the glory of the Lord is departed from you:<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48789:13"/>becauſe you have forſaken your firſt love: to wit, the true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and breathings after God in ſincerity: that was (I <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>) in many of you about 12 years ago. Wo is me for youl who were as it were perſecuted for Chriſts ſake; and now are turned perſecutors; as will be made appear as followeth. For if the Lord ſend any of his innocent ſervants amongſt you to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon, you cry out, <hi>you are diſturbed,</hi> Prieſt-like: limiting the Spirit of the Lord to an hour Glaſs: Or if any ſpeak a word, as moved of the Lord in the time you are ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the divination of your own brains, then ſome of you have laid violent hands, and haled out of doors, and ſhut the door: this many of you in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> can witneſs; Oh trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tremble, and be aſhamed ye careleſs ones I many days ſhall ye be troubled, the mouth of the Almighty have ſpoken it: And in the Light of the Son of God examine your ſelves: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches and friendſhip of the world, which is enmity unto God, and the glory of the world, have not blinded the eye of your underſtanding, and ſo <hi>Adam</hi> the old man by the earthly mindedneſs hath ſtopt up, or choaked that of God in you, which ſhould give you the true knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt; which if ever ye Baptiſts come to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of in truth, by the powerfull operation of Gods Spirit working in you, muſt you feelingly know through judgement that part removed, till that which cannot be ſhaken, be raiſed in dominion to raign in you: for yet once more will the Lord by his mighty power ſhake, not onely the earth, but heaven al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And will ye nill ye, ſhall ye all know, (who are of Gogs number making war againſt the Lamb and his followers) a Day of quaking:
<hi>for in my jealouſie, and the fire of my wrath, have I ſpoken,</hi> ſaith the Lord; <hi>Surely in that day there ſhall be a great ſhaking, ſo that the Fiſhes of the Sea, the fowls of the heaven; and the beaſts of the field, and all creeping things, that creep upon the earth: and all men that are upon the face of the earth, ſhall ſhake at my preſence: and the mountains ſhall be thrown down, and the ſteep places, and walls ſhall fall to the ground, and I will call for a ſword againſt him throughout all my mountains,</hi> ſaith the Lord God, <hi>every mans ſword againſt his Brother, and I will plead against him with pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence and blood, and rain great hailſtones, ſire and brimſtone: thus<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48789:14"/>will I magnifie my ſelf and ſanctifie my ſelf: and I will be known in the eyes of all Nations; and they ſhall know, that I am the Lord, Ezek.</hi> 38.19. to the end; So the judgement of Captain <hi>Sam. Wade</hi> concerning the firſt riſe of quaking; and magnifying the Light within, to be in oppoſition to the Scriptures, is altogether proved falſe, and a Spiritual deluſion. This have I written only for the ſake of the ſimple: &amp; the clearing of falſe reports againſt the truth; and thoſe that have deſires after it, God knows I lye not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>5 The Principles and Judgement of <hi>Joſeph Parſons,</hi> Paſtor and Teacher to thoſe people called
<hi>Freewillers;</hi> he affirmed before his flock;—<hi>That the Lord would purge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Tribe of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> to offer ſacrifices and offerings;</hi>—I demanded whether he meant Carnall ſacrifices, &amp;c. to wit the blood of bulls and goats, &amp;c. as in the Leviticall Prieſthood; he anſwered—<hi>Yea, as in the former days of old; and as in the years paſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here <hi>Joſeph Parſons</hi> would go to make Chriſt, the one offering <hi>(by which he hath for ever perfected them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied)</hi> to be of none effect; by which one offering, he changed both Law and Prieſthood; diſannulled the Commandements, which ſtood in meats and drinks and Carnall waſhings, and the ſacrificing and offering of the blood of bulls and goats, &amp;c. which never made thoſe that were the actors thereof, clean or perfect: as pertaining to the conſcience: which were but types and figures, and ſtood in time, and had a limitation of time; to wit, till the time of reformation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9.10 and though there was a time, the Lord had regard unto thoſe ſacrifices,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that they were as a ſweet ſavour unto him, and he delighted in them, and in thoſe that offered them. Yet when their hearts went a whoring after other lovers, And turned that which once the Lord required of them, into Idolatry, then the Lord loathed it, and them; and their ſolemnities-were a burden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; and he ſent his Prophets, riſing early to cry againſt them: And by the mouth of the Prophets, the Lord told them, <hi>he had not required theſe things at their hands, but it was abomination unto him, Iſa.</hi> 1.11. <hi>to the</hi> 15. As ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have not cauſed thee O</hi> Jacob, <hi>to ſerve with offerings: neither haſt thou honoured me with thy ſacrifices; but thou haſt made me to ſerve with thy ſins:</hi> as <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48789:14"/>ſaith the Apoſtle,
<hi>Sacrifices and Carnall offerings thou wouldeſt not O God, but a body haſt thou prepared me &amp;c.</hi> So that when that body of Chriſt Jeſus was offered up; which came to do the will of God according as it was written in the Volume of the Book he <hi>(mark)</hi> for ever perfected and ſanctified them; which believed and followed him, and changed that Law and Prieſthood, and is the end of it for righteouſneſs ſake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo I ſay, if the work of Chriſt in this the mighty day of his Power and Judgement, in which he is come and coming as a refiners fire to purge and purifie the Sons of <hi>Levy:</hi> that they might offer an offering in righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay if it were to offer Carnall Sacrifices as in the days of old, it would be a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again that which he hath changed, <hi>and I ſaith the Lord, change not,</hi> but the Apoſtles <hi>(amongſt whom that day of Judgement firſt began) for one day is with the Lord as a thouſand years, &amp;c. they</hi> plainly ſhews what that offering was: which the Prophet <hi>Mal.</hi> ſpoke of which ſhould be pleaſant; unto the Lord as in the days of old, and in former years,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſaith the Apoſtle to them which had taſted that the Lord was gracious; <hi>ye alſo as Living ſtones, are built up,</hi> (take notice of the offering that ſhould bee pleaſant) <hi>&amp;c. a ſpirituall houſe, an holy Prieſthood to offer up ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſacrifices: acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> this was, and is, the everlaſting offering that is offered up by the members of the Church and firſt fruits unto God ſince the long night of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, who as living ſtones are built up a ſpirituall houſe, a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prieſthood, a holy nation, a peculiar people, that the Lord hath called out of darkneſs into the marvellous Light; to ſhew forth his praiſe who hath lead and is leading through the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the fire: whereby <hi>(bleſſing and glory, glory to the Lord in the higheſt;)</hi> many are purged and purified; even as fine gold; through which they are come into the pure Life of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, from which an offering, a ſweet odour, a ſavour accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto the Lord, as in the days of old, and years paſt, in righteouſneſs is offered unto the Lord. So
<hi>Joſeph Parſons</hi> hath manifeſted himſelf, to be amongſt the Babyloniſh fooliſh build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and ignorant of the Scriptures: not dividing the word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: The words of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> are fulfilled in the Paſtors: for ſaith he, <hi>the Paſtors are become brutiſh, and have not</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48789:15"/>known the Lord in rightouſneſs, <hi>therefore they ſhall not proſper, and all their flocks ſhall be ſcattered, Jer.</hi> 10.21.</p>
               <p>And when the Prophet ſpoke of that day of the Lord, in which the Lord would be (and now is) a ſwift witneſs againſt the forcerer, the falſe prophet, and falſe ſwearers, adulterers and oppreſſors, &amp;c. and alſo of the offering that ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, &amp;c. He doth not ſpeak there of the Carnall offerings of the Leviticall Prieſthood, but of the offerings of <hi>Judah, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.4.</note> And the Scripture ſaith it is evident that our Lord ſprungout of
<hi>Judah;</hi> of which there was nothing ſpoke concerning Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; So this day that Scripture is fulfilled in your ears, for the offering of
<hi>Judah,</hi> according to the Spirit: and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is come down from God out of heaven, and is free, the mother of us all, is pleaſant unto the Lord, as in the days of old and years paſt, compare <hi>Mat.</hi>
3.4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.25.26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. And they are not all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who are of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the fleſh; but they are of the true <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that are born of the immortall Word of God that lives and abides for ever; in whoſe mouth is found no guile, neither tells a lye: and hee made all nations on the face of the whole earth, of one fleſh and blood;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 5
<hi>Act.</hi> 17.26.</note> and in Chriſt Jeſus there is no difference, whether Jew or Gentile, male or female, circumciſion, uncircumciſion, Barbarian, Scythian, bond or free, <hi>for ye (mark that) are all one in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Col.</hi>
3.11. for <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh ſtumbled at Chriſt the chief corner ſtone, as many of the Paſtors and Teachers now do, at Chriſt the Light within; ſo he is not a Jew, who is one outwardly, but he is a true Jew who is one inwardly, following the Lamb in the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe praiſe is of God, and not of man; yet a bundantly will the Lord be glorified, in the Jews according to the fleſh, the day of whoſe redemption draws near, and their captivity haſtneth to be at an end; and that is the Word of the Lord God of hoſts to the Jews.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>6 The raſh Judgement of <hi>William Lee</hi> Baptiſt Teacher, Governour of <hi>Waterford</hi> reproved and found falſe, and ſo proved according to the Law and Teſtimony; wherein alſo is a true teſtimony, of the operation of the eternall power and Spirit of the Lord, in the work of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:48789:15"/> On the 4 day of the 6 month 1659. I being at <hi>And. Richets</hi> houſe, then Mayor of <hi>Waterford,</hi> about my releaſing out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being, then a priſoner for the teſtimony of Jeſus. And there being preſent he called <hi>Colenell William Lee,</hi> and
<hi>William Lamb</hi> a Baptiſt Paſtor, this did occaſion ſome conference about the things of God: I earneſtly contending for the faith of Gods Elect once delivered to the Saints; which gives victory over ſin and bearing my teſtimony to Gods righteous Law and Spirit of Truth in man; which largely afore is proved by the Scriptures of truth, for all men by it to be guided; having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a meaſure thereof; this was the ſubſtance of what I there declared. That of God in them bears me record; which is the everlaſting truth of God.</p>
               <p>But <hi>William Lee</hi> Teacher, and <hi>William Lamb</hi> Paſtor, ſtrongly oppoſed me, crying out, <hi>The Ordiances of Chriſt: The Ordinances of Chriſt:</hi> to wit, <hi>the Supper of the Lord, and water Baptiſm,</hi> which ſtood in time, and were Ordinances of God and Chriſt; But had a limitation of time, and are ended in Chriſt the everlaſting ſubſtance, to every one that believes and follows, as will be proved by the Scriptures of truth;</p>
               <p>So he call'd Colonell <hi>Will. Lee,</hi> governour and Baptiſt Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, affirmed in the preſence of <hi>Will. Lamb</hi> Paſtor, the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Aldermen</hi> ſo called, and ſeverall
<hi>Captains</hi> and other men of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the worlds account, both
<hi>Baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Independants</hi>—<hi>That I was abſolutely damned and did not believe the truth; nor abide in the Doctrine and Ordinances of Chriſt</hi>—</p>
               <p>Now I appeal to Gods witneſs in the conſciences of all who cry out that the Quakers do Judge; when did any of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>(that are ſo in truth;)</hi> give ſuch raſh Judgement as to ſay any man was abſolutely damned; which is a ſecret belonging onely to God, except the unbeliever confeſs it out of his own mouth; or that the fruits of his Life make it appear?</p>
               <p>But bleſſed be the Lord God and Father of Light, through his eternall Love in Chriſt Jeſus, I do believe, and follow the Truth, which is Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the world, that Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every one that comes into the world; and am dead with Chriſt, buried with him in Baptiſm in meaſure, and cannot bee ſubject to Ordinances that periſh in the uſing; and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48789:16"/>and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that believes not ſhall be damned. And this teſtimony I give to all the world, and ſons of men, on the face of the whole earth. I do believe that Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the ſouls of mankind, was the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Son of God, born of a Virgin; whoſe name and interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I truly in my meaſure witneſs, even the Emmanuel, God with us; who made a good confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> that he was Crucified and Buried, and by the mighty Power and Glory of God the Father of Life, was raiſed again, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto his Diſciples and was received up to eternall Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Glorified with the Father, with the ſame Glory he had before the world began; And much more do I believe in him and of him; according as it is recorded in the holy Scriptures of Truth concerning him, which I may not now declare.</p>
               <p>And this Teſtimony I give for the Lord God, and his truth, unto all who have breathings after Chriſt, and are hungering and thirſting after his righteouſneſs; But are gazing abroad and ſeeking him in outward obſervations, &amp;c. that Chriſt Jeſus the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the quickning Spirit, is come the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation, in his choſen thouſands: Therefore turn in your mindes to that of God in you,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the woman that loſt the groat and could not find it, untill ſhe had Lighted a Candle <hi>(the Candle of the Lord is the Spirit of man: the Light of Chriſt Lightneneth it)</hi> and ſwept her houſe, and when ſhe found it, ſhe called her Neighbours and rejoiced; read the Parable who can.</p>
               <p>And I can truly ſay, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, he is come to ſave ſinners of which I was chief; which lived in Pride, Luſt, Vanity, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming his holy name, but have obtained mercy becauſe it was in the time of ignorance and unbelief; not through works that I have done, but of his everlaſting free Love; Yet have born his Juſt and Righteous Judgements, and deeply have drank of the cup of his fierce wrath and indignation; and can truly ſay, I am waſhed, cleanſed, ſanctified and Juſtified <hi>(in my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure)</hi> by the water, the blood and the Spirit; which three agree in one, in the work of regeneration, and ſo through the faith of God; which works by love, am brought in obedience to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and his commands, and in it to abide, and<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48789:16"/>this is his Doctrine:
<hi>Bleſſed be the poor in Spirit, bleſſed be the meek, bleſſed be they that mourn, &amp;c.</hi> Thou <hi>haſt heard that it hath been ſaid of old time thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelfe; but I ſay unto you ſwear not at all; and when thou prayeſt, be not like the Hypocrites which ſtand praying</hi> (in Pulpits) <hi>and call no man maſter, neither be ye called of man maſter; and Love your enemies, give to him that asketh, and from him that would borrow, turn not away, that you may be children of your heavenly Father; for he maketh his Sun to ſhine on the evill, and on the good, and ſendeth rain on the Juſt and unjuſt: and he that looketh on a woman to Luſt after her, hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Committed adultry with her in his heart, &amp;c. And lay not up for your ſelves treaſure in the earth, where the moth and Canker do cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; but lay up for your ſelves, treaſure in heaven, where neither moth nor ruſt do corrupt, nor thievs break through and ſteal. And I ſay unto you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ſwear not at all, but in all your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, let your</hi> yea, <hi>be</hi> yea, <hi>and your</hi> nay
<hi>be</hi> nay; <hi>for whatſoever is more then that, cometh of evill; and take no thought what ye ſhall eat, or what ye ſhall drink, or wherewithall ye ſhall be cloathed; and take no thought for to morrow, But firſt ſeck the Kingdom of God, and his righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And be ye perfect even as your heavenly Father is perfect;</hi> and his Miniſters bid
<hi>try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, flee youthfull Luſts of Vanity, abſtain from every ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill, quench not the Spirit; but if any thing be revealed to him that ſtands by, let the firſt hold his peace, &amp;c.</hi> Now whether thou <hi>William Lee</hi> and ye Baptiſts, which cry out, <hi>the Ordinances of Chriſt, and the Commands of Chriſt,</hi> be in the obedience to thoſe weightier Commands and Ordinances, which is fulfilled through faith, mercy, and Judgement upon the head of the tranſgreſſor, I ſay whether you Baptiſts, or we deſpiſedly called <hi>Quakers,</hi> be in the obedience to thoſe Commands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And many other which might be mentioned, of Chriſt, and his Miniſters, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides in their Doctrine: Let that of God in all Judge, which the leaſt of thoſe, or any of his Commands knowningly or will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I dare not diſobey, if I might gain the whole world, God is my record, I lye not, <hi>And he that ſaith he knows God</hi> (mark that you Baptiſts) <hi>and keepeth not his Commandements, is a lyar, and the truth is not in him,</hi> 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.4. So the truth of Chriſt, and his Doctrine, I do believe, and abide in: through his mercy and Power.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48789:17"/>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But thou doſt not practice the Ordinances of bread, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of water. Well, let us reaſon together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I do require and challenge all the
<hi>Baptiſts</hi> in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to prove by expreſs words, <hi>(for he that addeth or diminiſheth to, or from the words written in the Booke, God will adde to him the Plagues written therein)</hi> where ever Chriſt did baptize with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or command any to baptize with Elementary Water; That
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28,19. <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> doth not ſpeak of Elementary Water; and it is evident, the Scripture doth ſpeak of other Baptiſm then <hi>John's,</hi> which was onely Elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Water, which I alſo do believ was a Command of God to <hi>John,</hi> though ſometimes practiſed by the Diſciples, but fulfilled, and ended by, and in Chriſt, to every one that believes and follows the Light of Chriſt within, which leads to the one Baptiſm, the weightier matter, ſpoken of
<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>And I have a Baptiſm to be baptized with,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and how am I ſtraitened ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, Luk.</hi>
12.50. Now Chriſt had fulfilled <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, as to himſelf, before he ſpoke thoſe words, and was before that ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized of
<hi>John,</hi> as you may read <hi>Luke</hi> 3.2. And himſelf did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie the decreaſing of his Miniſtration; For (ſaith he) <hi>I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize with water unto repentance; but he that cometh after me, who is mightier then</hi> I, <hi>he ſhall baptize you with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire:</hi> He doth not ſay, Chriſt ſhould baptize with Water, but with the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>he ſhall encreaſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>John</hi>) <hi>but</hi> I <hi>ſhal decreaſe.</hi> And when the Apoſtle came to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> finding certain Diſciples which had
<hi>(take notice)</hi> been baptized before that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>John,</hi> he ſaid unto them, Have ye received the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed? And they ſaid, We have not ſo much as heard, whether there be any Holy Ghoſt, Then ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> (<hi>who was not ſent to baptize with water; for I baptized none, ſaith he, except</hi> Criſpus and <hi>Paulus, &amp;c. and the houſhold of</hi> Stephanus) To what were ye baptized? They ſaid, Unto
<hi>John,</hi> Then ſaith he, <hi>John verily baptized with the Baptiſm of Repentance,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That they ſhould believe on him that ſhould come after him, Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> When they heard that, they were baptized into Chriſt; and <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands on them, and they received the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.1. to the 6. So it is evident, as I ſaid before, there is another Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm then Water-Baptiſm, as true experience of many can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48789:17"/>who are now baptiſed, and baptizing into the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, or into Chriſts death, according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth; for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Know ye not, that ſo many of us, as have been baptized into Chriſt, were baptized into his death, &amp;c. Rom.</hi> 6.3. And he ſaid unto the <hi>Galatians, As many of you as have been Baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.27. So the Scripture doth not ſay, any where, that they that are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into the Father, are baptized with water, or they that are baptized into the Son and Holy Ghoſt are baptized with Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary water, which onely was a type or figure of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing, and ſanctifying; for the baptiſme of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, is three diſtinct things, of a various ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, though wrought by one and the ſame ſpirit; the one, a miniſtration of <hi>Terror</hi> and <hi>Condemnation;</hi> the ſecond, of
<hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or waſhing and cleanſing from ſin; and the third, a
<hi>Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and Glorifying, with the ſame Glory, that was with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the world or ſin began. And ſo I do affirm in the fear of the Lord, which is according to the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>That Chriſt is the end of the Law, and of</hi> John's <hi>miniſtration for righteouſneſs ſake, to every one that believes in the Light, which Chriſt hath enlightned every one withall;</hi> that whoſoever (I ſay) believes in the Light of Chriſt in them, it leads, as they follow it into the one baptiſm,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5: and daily Croſs of Chriſt, to the Crucifying and ſlaying, of the Luſts of the fleſh, Pride of Life, envyings, wrath, ſtrife, adulteries, Idolatry, witchcraft, variance, emulation, ſeditions, hereſie, Drunkenneſs, murders, ſelf-willedneſs, &amp;c. the which they that live in, are not Chriſts, neither are ſuch actions the fruits of the members of the true Church; And whether many of thoſe ſins be not ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you Baptiſts, Let that of God in you all Judge: for I, ſtanding peaceably in a meeting, amongſt the Baptiſts in
<hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> where <hi>William Lee</hi> was Preaching; and when he had done, I ſtood upon a form to ſpeak the Word of the Lord that was in my heart, as fire, deſiring their moderation, I ſpeaking no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things then what is contained in the Scriptures of Truth; but <hi>Will. Lee</hi> came out of his Pulpit, and laid violent hands on me, and thruſt me down, gnaſhing his teeth on me. Another member of that Church, <hi>Serjeant Wilſon,</hi> Conſtable of the Town,<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48789:18"/>laid violent hands on me, and haled me out of the room, and ſaid, That I deſerved to be ſtoned to death; and another time, I walking peaceably in the next room to their meeting, came
<hi>Geo. Caldron,</hi> called an <hi>Alderman,</hi> and told me, It was their hired houſe, and if I did ſtay there, it ſhould be to my perill; and the day aforeſaid, when I was with the <hi>Mayor,</hi> when <hi>Will. Lamb Paſtor</hi> was taking his leave of the <hi>Mayor,</hi> he bowed hat and knee, ſaying—<hi>Your humble ſervant Sir</hi>—according to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the world which paſſeth away; for which I reproving him, he came and laid hands on my hat, and took it off my head, and threw it violenton the ground; which ſome of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would have had him taken up again, but he would not; ſo becauſe I know they were aſhamed of the brutiſhneſs of their Paſtor, one of them took up my hat and ran after me, and put it on my head, which was ſaid to be <hi>Captain Boulton;</hi> And that ſame day, becauſe I teſtified the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles were not the Word of God, but I ſaid that which was ſpoken from the Spirit of God, were the Words of God; but Chriſt is the Word,
<hi>Bov.</hi> 19. <hi>Jo.</hi> 1.1. So <hi>Will. Lamb</hi> was ſpeaking with the reſt, and would have had me to been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of, for he ſaid there was an Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould ſay the Scripture was not the Word of God, they ſhould ſuffer, &amp;c. And being ſomtime after that, amongſt the Baptiſts of <hi>Waterford, Jo. Deck</hi> a Teacher of them, was whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering with ſome of his Brethren, and came preſently unto me, and held up the Bible in his hand, and asked me.—<hi>whether that was not the Word of God?—Judas</hi>-like to betray or inſnare me; I asked him whether that was the Word of God, which <hi>Rabſhaka</hi> and
<hi>Sennacherib ſpoke,</hi> blaſpheming and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the Living God, and that the Devil ſpoke to Chriſt? his anſwer was—<hi>That it was</hi>—; And <hi>Roger Mokell,</hi> which that day was preaching, I being moved of the Lord to give my teſtimony againſt him, which by good and fair words <hi>(they were good words us they were ſpoken from the holy men of God, but the deceiver taking them to cover his deceit)</hi> thereby deceives the ſimple; ſo after that, in my conference with <hi>R. M.</hi> he ſaid he had not an Infallible Spirit, but was ſubject to erre; ſo this makes good my teſtimony for the Lord, that he ſpoke not<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48789:18"/>from the mouth of the Lord, but ſpoke the good words, as I ſaid before, from an erring ſpirit; for all that ſpeak not from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſpirit, or meaſure thereof, ſpeak from an erring ſpirit: So let that of God in all Judge, what Paſtors &amp; Teachers theſe be; Many other ſuch like paſſages might I relate, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would be too large to write, neither do I write it out of prejudice or envy unto any, God knows I lye not; but it is only that all who are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, may throughly ſearch themſelvs, &amp; with that of God in them, ſee, what they have Profited in the things of God, by ſuch Paſtors and Teachers, and into what you are baptized; for where the old man and its fruits are ſtanding; to wit, Pride, Luſt, Envy, &amp;c. You are not come ſo far as <hi>John's</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme the true figure, which was to repentance, nor the anſwer of a good conſcience, by the reſurrection of the Juſt; but have need to be taught the firſt Principles of the true Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; to wit, turn to the Light of Chriſt in you, which would lead you to repentance and from dead works, &amp;c. and to go on to perfection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.2. And into the daily Croſs, as I ſaid afore, to the crucifying of the old man and his deeds, and ſo to know as
<hi>Panl</hi> did, a daily dying, and baptized into the death of Chriſt, buried with him in baptiſm; that Like as Chriſt, was raiſed by the Power and Glory of God the Father of Life, from the Grave, ſo to be raiſed and changed, into newneſs of Life, and ſo the fruits and effects of the Spirit of Truth will be brought forth; which are meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, Brotherly kindneſs, Gentleneſs, Temperance, Love, Faith, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt: Now if theſe fruits and effects are brought forth by you Baptiſts, let that of God in all Judge: for Chriſt ſaid, <hi>falſe Prophets ſhould come, and ye ſhall know them by their fruits,</hi> and now falſe Prophets and brutiſh Paſtors are known by their fruits, who cry out, <hi>the Ordinances of Chriſt. The Ordinances of Chriſt! &amp;c.</hi> Even as the falſe Prophets did in the days of old, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of Lord,</hi> but mocked the meſſengers of the Lord God, and deſpiſed his Words, and killed and miſ-uſed his Prophets; againſt ſuch Chriſt himſelf cryed, and Propheſied the deſtruction of that Temple, and ſaid, <hi>God his Father was a Spirit, and in the Spirit, and in the Truth would he be worſhipped,</hi> And told his Diſciples when he was with them, <hi>That except he did go away, the Comforter<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48789:19"/>would not come, But if he did go away, he would ſend the Comforter, even the Spirit of Truth which ſhould lead and guide them into all Truth, and ſhew them things to come.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p n="8">8 Therfore that very night he was betrayed, as a Pledge of his Love, knowing that his Diſciples were but weak <hi>(The Holy Ghoſt not being then given amongſt them)</hi> though he had done many glorious works and miracles amongſt them, he left them a remembrance of himſelf, which was the figure of the Spirituall breaking of Bread, as will be ſhewed; I ſay, that very night Chriſt was betrayed, <hi>He took Bread and broke it, and bleſſed it,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This is my Body, which is broken for many, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Likewiſe the Cup,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, &amp;c.</hi> which was to be done <hi>onely in remembrance of him,</hi> ſaith <hi>the Apoſtle,</hi> (mark the Limitation of time) <hi>till he come;</hi> who bleſſed be the Lord many do witneſs to be come in great Power &amp; Glory, and when his good Spirit was come unto the Apoſtles, it was their great work to bring the Saints off, from outward things that were ſeen, Carnall Ordinances that periſhed in the uſing; for Bread is ſeen, and Wine is ſeen, and Elementary Water is ſeen, and they all are Carnall, and periſh in the uſing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.18.
<hi>Col.</hi> 2.22. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>If ye be dead with Chriſt, why as though Living, are ye Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Ordinances which all are to periſh in the uſing after the Commandements of men?</hi> threrefore he bid them <hi>beware, Leaſt any man ſpoyle them through Philoſophy and vain deceit, and traditions of men, after the rud ments of the world, and not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, Col.</hi> 2.8. to the end of the <hi>Chap.</hi> And bid them <hi>if they were riſen with Chriſt, to ſeek thoſe things which were above</hi> Carnall Ordinances which periſhed in the uſing, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And this teſtimony I give to all the world, That you bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and other, that are found practiſing thoſe ordinances, Baptiſm, and breaking Bread, &amp;c. you are not to be parallel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or compared to the Saints and Apoſtles, that did practiſe thoſe things, in their purity or firſt inſtitution by Chriſt, &amp; not from tradition or command of mans for whatever Chriſt or his Prophets or holy Apoſtles did practiſe, as is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Scripture, is no ground for any one now to practiſe, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48789:19"/>except commanded or moved immediately, by the ſame ſpirit that lead them unto it; for they that ſo do, will be found in the rudiments of the World, walking in traditions, &amp; although they may ſay, They have eaten and drunken at the Table of the Lord, and propheſied in his Name, and done many wonders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet when God's righteous Witneſs comes to be raiſed in Power to judgement, it will be ſaid,
<hi>Who required thoſe things at your hands, &amp;c?</hi> For ſince the long Night of Apoſtaſie that Antichriſt hath reigned, through his ſubtil working, hath gotten into all theſe outward Ordinances, Practiſes, and Forms that were pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by the Primitive Church, but the Power he had not, which did then, even in the dayes of the Apoſtles, begin to work with all Power, Signs and lying Wonders, in them that periſh; whom now by the ſecond and glorious appearance of Chriſt in man is revealing the man of ſin, and Myſtery of Iniquity, and by the Power of his Spirit, and brightneſs of his coming, is deſtroying and conſuming of him, which hath a long time reigned in man, the Temple of God: And therefore ye Baptiſts, you are found in the Traditions and Rudiments of the World; for the Pope, Jeſuits, and all his Fryars, and all that they call Chriſtendom, are baptizing and breaking bread, crying out, The Ordinances of the Lord,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Spirit of Life from God, which is eternal, and not carnal, nor ſeen with the carnal eye; he, I ſay, that hath this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is come to the end of all thoſe ſhadows, and knows himſelf as he abides in it, a member of the body of which Chriſt is the the Head, and a member of the true Church in God, with the Saints in Light, and ſo comes truly to ſay, as the Apoſtles did, <hi>We being many, are one body, and one bread;</hi> I ſpeak as to the wiſe in God, to judge what I ſay: <hi>The Cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the Blood, the Life of Jeſus Chriſt? And the Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? &amp;c. For all are partakers of that one Bread; I am the Bread of Life,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he that hath an ear to hear, let him hear; and he that eats thereof, ſhall never dye:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>I</hi> ſay, in this the day of God's eternal Power, his children who meet together, ſitting in the heavenly high places, waiting on the Lord in the meaſure of his ſpirit, and in the Spirit of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48789:20"/>Truth are worſhipping him; they being many are one body, and come to be partakers of that ſpiritual Bread of life, which is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken amongſt them by the Divine hand, through the Power of the Lord, &amp; ſo are come to the ſubſtance of the ſhadow or outward ſign, which was to be done in remembrance by the Diſciples, till he come, <hi>&amp;c. (but not commanded to be practiſed by ſucceeding Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as a traditional rudiment)</hi> the which did prefigure the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual communion of the Saints, in the diſpenſation of times, which is come, for the gathering together all in one, even in CHRIST, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. And thoſe that were baptized unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c.</hi> They alſo eat of this Spiritual Bread, and drank of that Spiritual Rock which followed them, and that Rock was Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.4. Therefore in the Power and Authority of the Spirit of the Lord, I bear teſtimony, That all the children of the Lord that are taught of him, and in his righteouſneſs, in their meaſures are eſtabliſhed, are come to the end of all thoſe ſhadows, types and figures, which ſtood in meats, drinks, and divers waſhings, and ſuch carnal Ordinances, baptiſing with Water, and breaking natural Bread,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Outward Offerings, and ſacrificing of Beaſts,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> are carnal, (and the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>I Paul testifie unto you, if you be circumciſed, Chriſt will profit you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> What Scripture had the Apoſtle to prove that, <hi>ſeeing there was a time Scripture required it?</hi>) I ſay, although theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and commands were inſtituted by the Father and the Son, they ſtood in time, until he that was before time, and for ever will remain, when time ſhall be no more, was manifeſt the ſecond time, <hi>&amp;c. even Chriſt in them the hope of glory;</hi> and he that believes, hath the witneſs of truth <hi>in himſelf,</hi> and ſo is come in truth, according to the Scriptures of truth, to the end of thoſe carnal Ordinances, which were impoſed on them (take notice of the limitation of time) until the time of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10,11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p n="9">9 And this teſtimony <hi>I</hi> give for the Lord's Truth, &amp; his choſen ones, whom he hath called to labour in his Vinyard, that we <hi>(called Quakers)</hi> do not deny the Ordinance of God &amp; Chriſt to wit, Baptiſm and breaking of bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they ſtood in their time and place, as is aforeſhewed; but for any to take them up, by tradition or imitation, (according to the Doctrine of<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48789:20"/>Paſtor <hi>Hunt</hi> Baptiſt, which ſaid in the high place in their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Kilkenny,—That none could follow Chriſt, to be as perfect as he was</hi>—Therefore ſaith he, <hi>They muſt be as perfect as they can, and follow him ſo well as they can, and by imitation</hi>—And ſo hee would make the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Miniſters, to be of none effect by his imitation and traditions; for his Doctrine and Miniſtry was for the perfecting of the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; they preacht wiſdom amongſt them that were perfect, and they laboured to preſent every man perfect in Chriſt; and <hi>Epaphras</hi> prayed they might ſtand perfect. And the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>They were compleat in Chriſt, and come to mount Sion, and to an innumerable company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> And Chriſt ſaid,
<hi>Whoſoever will be my Diſciple, he muſt take up his dayly Croſs and follow me:</hi> He doth not ſay—<hi>Follow me as well you can, &amp;c.</hi> but his Diſciples ſaid, <hi>We have followed thee in the regeneration, &amp;c.</hi> and they received the Light of Life through which they loved one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and ſaid, <hi>Herein was their love made perfect, and therein was their boldneſs, becauſe even as he was</hi> (mark the reaſon) <hi>in the day of Judgement, even ſo were they in the preſent,</hi> and were and are perfect; and ſo they witneſſed his Command and Doctrine ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, which ſaid, <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your heavenly Father is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> And for any, as I ſaid before, to take up any Ordinance, (except moved of the Lord by imitation or tradition, I manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm, It is abſolute Idolatry and Witchcraft, drawing the minds of creatures into outward obſervations, contrary to the law &amp; Teſtimony; and that is the only Work of Antichriſt, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Lo here, lo there;</hi> (and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Go not forth</hi>) to keepe the minds of creatures in outward things, which periſh in the uſing, from the Light of the Son of God within, which he hath enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened every one that comes into the world withall, that all men through him might believe and walk in the Light, which would lead unto the one baptiſm, to be baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire, through which the heart comes to be purified, and the Faith of God's elect comes to be received, which gives the victory over the world, and the mercy and peace from God comes abundantly to be multiplied in, and on the new creature, who is changed and raiſed to newneſs of life by the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and glory that raiſed the Lord Jeſus from the Grave. So in<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48789:21"/>the Light of the Son of God, examine your ſelves ye Baptiſts, whether you are come to know a real change of life, and to be new creatures, and old things paſt a way, or paſſing away; if not, I teſtifie unto you in the Name of the moſt High God, your bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm avails you nothing and you are not yet come to the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance not to be repented of. And as ſure as the Lord lives, his juſt and righteous Judgement muſt you all come to feel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in you and upon that nature that hath diſobeyed his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, through which Gods Righteouſneſs comes to be revealed from Faith to Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> through which Revelation of his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgements in flames of fire, comes the creature to know the purging away the filth of the fleſh, and the conſuming of the man of ſin, which hath a long time ſate in the Temple of God, and exalted himſelfe above God, even the myſtery of iniquity comes to be revealed, which hath a long time reigned through the Power of darkneſs, which hath wrought with ſigns and lying wonders, which <hi>(glory, glory for ever to the Lord)</hi> he is now conſuming with the Spirit of his Wrath, and the brightneſs of his coming, 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and look within; for all your preaching, and praying, and ſeeming holineſs, being not moved or guided by, and from the ſpirit of the Lord, is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickedneſs, which the Apoſtles vvarred againſt, vvhoſe Weapons vvere not carnal, as theirs are that lay violent hands on the creature, and vvould have ſtoned him to death.</p>
               <p>And ſo, vvill ye, nill ye, a day of ſilence <hi>(if ever you come to enjoy the Lords Truth, in the truth of it)</hi> ſhall you knovv, that is Gods truth to you all; For your prayers and ſacrifices are as the ſtrange fire unto the Lord, that vvas offered by <hi>Nadab</hi> and
<hi>Abihu,</hi> (mark) vvhich he commanded them not, for vvhich fire vvent forth from the Lord, &amp; devoured them, that they dyed before the Lord; and for that very cauſe <hi>(God beareth me record)</hi> vve the ſervants of the Lord, vvhen moved of him to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, cannot joyn or bovv to your imaginary prayers, in vvhich time ſome or moſt of you are ſitting at eaſe, and the Paſtor or Teacher, ſtanding praying many times in a Pulpit,
<hi>(Prieſt-like, taking a Text of Scripture, preaching by an hour-Glaſs)</hi> and ſo you plainly ſhevv you are not come in righteouſneſs to glorifie God vvith one mouth, and one mind; for vvhen your
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48789:21"/>Teacher ſtands praying and you fitting, it is a true teſtimony, you are not brought into the true humility; <hi>(but are in the ſtubborn rebellious nature; at eaſe in Sion, which the wo is to)</hi> nor to the Covenant of Life to perform, and fulfill the oath of God, which ſaid,
<hi>As I Live,</hi> (mark ye ſtiffe necked) <hi>every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue ſhall confeſs unto me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> and the Apoſtles and members of the true Church kneeled down to prayer by the Sea ſhore.</p>
               <p>And ſo I ſay, it is not out of contempt as to your Perſons, or as denying prayer, that we cannot join with you in it, as is afore ſhewed, for the prayers of the faithfull as the Lord leads to it, by and from the breathings, and movings of his eternall Spirit, we own in all humility, as may be expreſſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea ſomtimes, God knows I lie not, were it not for giving and offending his holy Spirit, for the oppreſſed ſeed ſake, that it might ariſe amongſt you, to praiſe the Lord, I could even bow down amongſt you, when the Lord hath ſent me amongſt you; but knowing the terrors of the Lord, and having felt his Righteous Judgements, and bore the Indignation of his wrath, dare not do it, but have many times ſtood bearing a heavy burden, a witneſs for the Lord againſt you. For <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the days of old, bowing to the Sacrifices of the Gods of <hi>Baal,</hi> the Anger of the Lord was therefore kindled againſt them, and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid unto the Judges of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the fierce anger of the Lord might be taken away, ſlay ye, ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> every one his men that were joined to <hi>Baalpeor, Numb.</hi> 25.1. to the 6. and therefore as I ſaid before, a day of ſilence, ſhall ye Baptiſts and all profeſſors of the earth know, that make mention of the name of the Lord but in the unrighteouſneſs which is ſin.</p>
               <p>The Lord God of heaven and earth hath a controverſie with you all, for your manifold tranſgreſſions, and for rejecting his counſell, and miſuſing his meſſengers which he hath ſent, riſing early, coming from far unto you, and you would none of his counſell, but hate and deſpiſe his ſervants, who reprove ſin in the gate, and you abhor them that ſpeak uprightly; Wo is me for you! my ſoul mourneth for you in ſecret; Oh! repent yee backſliders repent ye backſliders, who have forſaken the Lord of Life, and have ſettled your ſelves on the Lees, and think in<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48789:22"/>your hearts becauſe many of you have gotten great poſſeſſions and treaſure in the earth, ye ſhall not be moved: Oh! again I ſay unto you, meet the Lord by ſpeedy repentance, before the day of your viſitation be paſt away, and you find not a day of repentance, though you ſeek it with tears as <hi>Eſau</hi> did; for the mighty day of the Lord God over all the world is come and coming, ſuch as hath not been known ſince the world began; a day, wherein your ſolemn ſolemnities, and breaking Bread that periſheth in the uſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will be a day of great and thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, felt even as the Egyptian darkneſs; in it your Prudent muſt keep ſilence, mourning even as a woman mourneth over her onely ſon, for he that formed the mountains and created the winds, and ſheweth to man his thoughts, will plead with you, and all fleſh by fire, and by ſword, and great will the ſlain of the Lord be, yea they ſhall caſt out their dead bodies, with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; for ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Let the wicked be put to ſilence, in the Grave; and all that makes mention of the name of the Lord our God, who is a conſuming fire, muſt depart from iniquity. And as you, and all people on the face of the earth, come to wait on the Lord in the way of his Judgements, you will ſenſibly come, truly and gladly to ſay, bleſſed be he that comes in the Truth, and in the name of the Lord, for he keepeth the feet of his Saints (mark that) but the wicked ſhall be ſilent in darkneſs: and <hi>David</hi> ſaid, Let the wicked lips be put to ſilence, (mark and take notice ye that deſpiſe the Light, and ſpeak proudly againſt the Light, and Spirit of God in man, to be the Rule and Guide of Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) That ſpeaketh proudly, grievous things, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly againſt the Righteous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.17.18. for the Lord is ariſen, and hath appeared in his Temple, Let the earth, and all fleſh keep ſilence before him; And therefore I ſay unto you, who deſpiſe the ſervants of the Lord, who preach ſilence to all fleſh, who ſit ſilently waiting on the Lord, ſpeaking as they are moved, if ever the true joy in God, you come to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of, it muſt be by returning in your minds into that of God in you, waiting in the ſilence of all fleſh; for let the Iſlands keep ſilence before me (mark) that the people may renew their ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.1. and thouſands who are come to know the honourable ſilent waiting on the Lord, do witneſs daily
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48789:22"/>ſtrength renewed. And when the ſeventh Seal was opened, there was ſilence in heaven halfe an hour; And ſo to preach ſilence to all fleſh, is according to the practiſe of the holy men of old; they ſpake as they were moved, of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they had received they miniſtered, as good ſtewards of the manifold gifts and graces of God, and Chriſt bid his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples go and wait at Jeruſalem, till they were indued with power from on high.</p>
               <p>And this hath been the ſubſtance of my teſtimony from the Lord unto you Baptiſts, That the Lord requires you to wait for the powerings forth of his eternall Spirit, and to feel its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and movings in you; untill then, in the dread, power and authority of the Spirit of the Lord, again I ſay unto you, Let all fleſh keep ſilence, Gods witneſs in every one of you ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally witneſs me to be true; for through the operation of Gods eternall Power and Spirit of Life; Life and Immortality is brought to Light, through which the Immortall ſoul comes to be refreſhed, and the ſeed of God raiſed out of death.</p>
               <p>And that Life and ſeed is but one in all, in the male and in the female, ſo if Gods Spirit move in ſon or daughter to ſpeak in the Church of Chriſt; it is not lawfull to quench it. But if any thing elſe ſpeak, whether in male or female, and not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord, or its movings, that which ſpeaks in male or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, being in the ſin and tranſgreſſion, that is the woman, or ſorrowfull ſinfull man, that muſt be ſilent, and ask the husband at home; which (if ſhe continue in the faith, Patience, Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sobriety, and Charity untill the man-child be born; or brought forth in Dominion to Raign, to Rule the tranſgreſſing part with a rod of Iron) ſhe may be ſaved: he that can receive it let him, for where ſin and evill is ſtanding, there is woe and ſorrow, whether in male or female; and all muſt be ſilent in the Church till ſin and iniquitie is blotted out; but who are come to know remiſſion of ſin, through faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, there is glad tidings, Joy and Peace, and all that ever mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, from the Spirit of Truth, in the Church of Chriſt, muſt firſt be a partaker of the fruits of the Kingdome of God in meaſure; for ſaith the Apoſtle, The husbandman that laboureth muſt firſt bepar taker of the fruits (<hi>viz.</hi> of that he miniſtereth,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48789:23"/>to wit, of the Joy or Glory he teſtifieth of) therefore ſaith he to <hi>Tymothy</hi> conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give thee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And male and female, is all one in Chriſt, and each muſt come to know the Travell and Anguiſh which makes all faces gather paleneſs, before that Child be brought forth: Wherefore ſaith the Prophet
<hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Ask ye now, and ſee whether a man doth travell with Child, wherefore do I ſee every man with his hands upon his Loins as a woman in travell, and all faces are turned into paleneſs, &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 30 6. This is a myſtery, Chriſt in man; And ſo I ſay, when the Life of Chriſt is brought forth in power, in ſon or daughter, it is Lawful for either to ſpeak in the Church of Chriſt, as <hi>Miriam</hi> and the holy women did, in the days of old, teach and inſtruct in the Congregation of the Lord, and <hi>Miriam</hi> taught <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſing praiſes to the Lord; and <hi>Deborah</hi> a Propheteſs Judged <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and inſtructed <hi>Barack</hi> &amp; taught the people to praiſe the Lord; and
<hi>Huldah</hi> the Propheteſs ſpoke the Word of the King, ſaying, Thus ſaith the Lord: And <hi>Priſcilla</hi> with <hi>Aquila</hi> her Husband, took <hi>Apollo</hi> a man of <hi>Alaxandria,</hi> and inſtructed him more perfectly in the way of the Lord; And <hi>Paul</hi> commends thoſe women to the <hi>Philippians</hi> which laboured with him in the Goſpell: And do the Baptiſts think the Apoſtle would commend thoſe women in one place, or to one people, and reprove them or write againſt them to another people, and command them to be ſilent; becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, I ſuffer not a woman to teach, or to uſurpe authority over the man, But be ſilent, and ask her Husband at home? &amp;c. and therefore you will not willingly (if the Lord ſend his handmaids or daughters amongſt you) ſuffer them to ſpeak, on whom the Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed he would pour out of his Spirit in the laſt days, and they ſhould Propheſie; I tell you there is a great miſtery in thoſe words, I ſuffer not a woman to teach, but to be in ſilence,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord of Hoſts is the Husband of his Church; and as
<hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaid, Our beloved brother <hi>Paul</hi> writ in all his Epiſtles ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned, in the Doctrine and myſteries of Chriſt; wreſt, as they do all other Scriptures, to their own deſtruction; Therefore take heed all ye that are ſtumbling at the Lords ſpeaking in his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids,<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48789:23"/>as in ages paſt, who is the ſame for ever. Leaſt yee are found perverting the Truth of the Lord, and quenching his Spirit; For <hi>Anna</hi> a Prophetteſs, a woman of great age, that had lived with an Husband, ſeven years from her Virginity; a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of about fourſcore years of age, that ſerved God in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings and Prayers, ſhe coming into the Temple, that inſtant when the Child Jeſus was in the Temple, ſhe gave thanks, and preached in the Temple redemption by Jeſus Chriſt to all them that looked for it, in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> And Chriſt himſelf, bid <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> to whom firſt he appeared after his Reſurrection, out of whom he had caſt ſeven Devills, Go and tell (or preach) to my Brethren, that he is ariſen, ſaith the Angell, and go to <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalee,</hi> there ſhal they ſee me, ſaith Chriſt; And ſo I ſay unto you, where ever the ſeed, which is Chriſt, to which all the promiſes of God are Yea and Amen (and all that ever come to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it muſt be in the ſeed) is brought forth in power to Raign, it is lawfull to ſpeak, whether in male or female: quench it not for in Chriſt Jeſus, there is no difference, in him all is one, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</p>
               <p>Therefore again I ſay unto you, quench not the Spirit of the Lord; but try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, and deſpiſe not reproof of Inſtruction, but receive the Truth in the Love of it, to wit, the Light, and Spirit of Truth within, as is largely before proved; according to the Scripture of Truth, as it is in Jeſus: And take heed, leaſt for your not receiving the Truth in the Truth, in the Love of it, God give you wholly over to reprobate minds, to work uncleanneſs with greedineſs and ſo he Juſtly ſend you ſtronger deluſions, that ye all may be damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! who will not believe, and receive the Truth in the Love of it; And then in that day of trouble and Anguiſh when you cry and call; even you who have cauſed the ſimple to erre, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in that which periſheth in the uſing, from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of of God in them, bringing all the Arguments and ſtrong Reaſons, to pervert and perſwade from the Truth, and to ſtop Gods Righteous witneſſe, from ariſing in the ſimple, of which many would hear and receive the Truth, but having not ſtrength are afraid of being caſt out from amongſt you, as it was amongſt the envious Jews, who ever of them did confeſs<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48789:24"/>Chriſt, was to be caſt out: But the day is near come, that ſuch fears ſhall be caſt out of them, who breath after God in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Truth, and they ſhall come to know one (if you caſt them out) will receive them; even as Chriſt received him, whom the Jews caſt out; and the Lord will bring them by a way they have not known, &amp; in paths they have not trodden (that which is high, rough, and crooked, will the Lord bring low, and make it ſtraight and plain) ſo that a fool ſhall not erre therein, and when the poor and needy ſeek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirſt, I the God of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Lord, will not forſake them, I will open rivers in high places, and fountains in the midſt of the Vallies, &amp;c.
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.17,18. And many of them which ye brutiſh Paſtors, &amp; Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, have kept in bondage, a Day when God's witneſs comes to be raiſed up in them in Power, a ſwift witneſs will the Lord make them againſt you, That is God's Truth unto you; and in that day, as I ſaid before, ſhall ye that have cauſed the ſimple to erre, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (Who are ſcorching in the flame and ye know it not, Gnaſhing and Blaſpheming God and his Tabernacle, who keep the Commands of Jeſus, according to the Law and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; to wit, the Light within, which is the Law, and the Spirit of Jeſus, which is the Teſtimony, by which his faithfull ones are moved and Guided; which you ſay, is the Spirit of the Devill, woe is me for you! cry unto the Lord, &amp; he wil not hear you, except ye ſpeedily Repent, to whom repentance is offered; for you would none of his reproof, neither did chooſe the pure fear of the Lord, but have hated the true knowledge of the Lord, and have choſen that wherein he delights not, but are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling, and rejecting the Counſell of the Lord, doing evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before me, ſaith the Lord. Therefore ſhal ye bow down to the ſlaughter, and my ſervants whom ye deſpiſe, ſhall eat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, and drink, and be ſatisfied, and ſing for Joy of ſoul; but you who are accounted as Embaſſadors of Peace, ſhal weep and howl for vexation of Spirit, and eat the fruit of your own doings, and not be ſatisfied; the mouth of the Lord hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it.</p>
               <p>Thus I have, in obedience to the movings of the Lord, in ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Love to all your ſouls; not ſhunned to declare and make<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48789:24"/>manifeſt the way to everlaſting ſalvation, as one that am truly ſenſible, of the ſtate, and want of Chriſt that all profeſſors of the world are in; I ſay unto every particular, whoſe deſires is after God, and would walk in the good old way, the way into it, is plainly made known, which is Jeſus Chriſt, the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which all that believe, &amp; follow, it will lead, in the daily Croſs of Chriſt, which will ſlay the enmity in man, which hath ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him from God, by which man, wil again come to an entrance into the everlaſting inheritance, to ſit down in our Fathers Houſe amongſt thoſe that are ſanctified, where is bread enough; And whereas thou <hi>Wil. Lee</hi> haſt ſaid, that I am abſolutely damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Is not the cauſe of Damnation unbelief, not believing in Chriſt the Light which Lighteth every one that comes into the world, which Light is within, and Spirit of Truth within, and Chriſt the hope of Glory within, except thou art a reprobate? &amp; whether the cauſe of
<hi>Judas</hi>'s damnation was not becauſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the Juſt into the hands of murderers? Therefore take heed <hi>Wil. Lee,</hi> that the Judgement thou &amp; others have given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Innocent, take heed it be not executed on your own pates; for thou and the reſt of you are in danger of it, becauſe ye have Judged before the time; for becauſe Judgement is not preſently executed, the miſery of man is great that goes on in his wickedneſs; take notice of that <hi>Wil. Lamb</hi> Paſtor, that boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Quakers had Judged thee long ago, and it is not yet come to paſs; for with what meaſure you have meted to others, will be meted to you again, good weight, preſſed down, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over, into your boſoms will men give unto you, and in the day of your perplexity remember you were forewarned in the Life time of your Proſperity.</p>
            </div>
            <argument>
               <p>Written in <hi>Clonmell</hi> the 8 month, 1659. when ye were at eaſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Peace and Safety. And had been publiſhed abroad long ere this time but Satan hath hindred, through keeping my body in bonds. Neither is it now publiſhed to exaſperate evill men againſt any of you Baptiſts, in this day of Tryall that is come, and yet more coming upon you; But it is laid on me, to ſet it forth, that ye may ſee how ye have rejected the Truth, and deſpiſed inſtruction, for which you muſt feel the hand of God. <hi>T. M.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
